<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of Scarbrough-Spaw, or, A further discovery of the excellent vertues thereof in the cure of the scurvy, hypochond. melancholy, stone, gonorrhea, agues, jaundies, dropsie, womens diseases, &amp;c. By many remarkable instances, being a demonstration from the most convincing arguments, viz. matter of fact. Also a discourse of an artificial sulphur-bath, and each of sea-water, with the uses thereof in the cure of many diseases. Together with a short account of other rarities of nature observable at Scarbrough. By W. Sympson doct. in physick.</title>
            <author>Simpson, William, M.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3832</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217885</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829528</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33968</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60266)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33968)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1980:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of Scarbrough-Spaw, or, A further discovery of the excellent vertues thereof in the cure of the scurvy, hypochond. melancholy, stone, gonorrhea, agues, jaundies, dropsie, womens diseases, &amp;c. By many remarkable instances, being a demonstration from the most convincing arguments, viz. matter of fact. Also a discourse of an artificial sulphur-bath, and each of sea-water, with the uses thereof in the cure of many diseases. Together with a short account of other rarities of nature observable at Scarbrough. By W. Sympson doct. in physick.</title>
                  <author>Simpson, William, M.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 96, 99-126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Simmons at the Princes Arms in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Diseases --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33968:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33968:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF SCARBROUGH-SPAW, OR, A further Diſcovery of the excellent Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues thereof in the Cure of the <hi>Scurvy, Hypochond. Melancholy, Stone, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norrhea, Agues, Jaundies, Dropſie, Womens Diſeaſes,</hi> &amp;c. By many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Inſtances, being a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the moſt convincing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>viz.</hi> Matter of Fact.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO</hi> A Diſcourſe of an Artificial <hi>Sulphur-Rath,</hi> and Bath of Sea-water, with the uſes thereof, in the cure of many Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With a ſhort account of other Rarities of Nature obſervable at <hi>Scarbrough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. Sympſon Doct. in Phyſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Simmons</hi> at the <hi>Princes Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33968:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33968:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Noble and moſt Honourable CHARLES PAWLET; Marqueſs of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> Earl of <hi>Wilt-ſhire,</hi> Baron St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Baſing, &amp;c.</hi> one of the Lords of his Majeſties moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Honour, <hi>My Lord,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not the leaſt amongſt thoſe Oriental Gems, which adorn the Breaſt of Nobility, nor ought it to be reputed the meaneſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Vertue, that by its lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre renders the minds of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſons truly ſuch, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be thought, but really to be encouragers of every gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb facs="tcp:33968:3"/>and uſeful undertaking; not barely in <hi>Specie</hi> but <hi>effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> to become Patrons to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry noble Deſign. And ſurely among the great variety of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks for diſcourſe (the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of things appertaining to another World, Divinity I mean excepted) none but in one ſence or other yields the Bayes to that highly uſeful one of health (with its Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Appendices) whether relating to the continuation or reſtauration thereof; to which our enſuing Hiſtory is ſo near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned as to merit the repute of being mainly intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductory thereto: whoſe adapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to humane neceſſities will
<pb facs="tcp:33968:3"/>evidently appear if we ſilently reſolve within our own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms the enſuing Queries, <hi>viz.</hi> What reſentment of Grandeur has an aching head, although encircled within the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Crown? What delight can a Stateſman take in Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating and ſetting at Rights the Grand Affairs of his Countrey while he labours under the Conſpiracy of prevalent, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though couchant, Maladies? What pleaſure hath a morbid and (therefore) diſguſtful Palate, the bane of Epicuriſm, in the fruition of the greateſt Delicacies, even amidſt the great variety which accoſts that erring ſenſual Organ?
<pb facs="tcp:33968:4"/>What profit can a Rich man take of all his wealth, while he labours under the pains of a Gouty fit? What quiet have we in the ſettlement of our Lands and Tenements; while the morbid Tenant we inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foſter, turns Lawyer and Bayliff too, ſues and turns us out of poſſeſſion by an irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible Leaſe of Ejectment? And in fine, what ſatisfaction have we of any thing we enjoy here below, while we truckle under any Grief or Malady? Now, my Lord, the generouſneſs of the Subject we treat upon, <hi>viz.</hi> The Hiſtory of theſe Mineral healing waters, is ſuch as (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other uſeful Eſſayes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:33968:4"/>a publick good) may from a ſolution of the aforeſaid Queries, as alſo from other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Arguments, deſervedly challenge your Honours Patro nage, in as much as you have been particularly pleaſed out of the ſence of that good you have experimentally reaped thereby to do that right to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Waters, as in the preſence of ſeveral worthy Perſonages publickly to own them, by giving this Autopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal teſtimony thereof (at leaſt what was equivalent thereto) That of all the Mineral waters you had taſted (few in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> or <hi>France</hi> having eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p'd your teſt) theſe of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33968:5"/>ſurpaſſed, both as to a thorow as well as effectual working: By which your Lordſhip received conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble relief the laſt Summer from the oppreſſing ſymptoms of the Hypochondraical wind, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at the lateſt ſeaſon of the year. — And, my Lord, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the following Tract as moſt-what grounded upon experience, (the mother of Knowledge) having its root deeply ſet in, and firmly knit upon, matter of Fact, is doubtleſs the better able to bear up, yea ſtand and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it ſelf againſt the ſhocks of any Calumniating Quill whatever; yet upon due and mature
<pb facs="tcp:33968:5"/>conſideration, there is much ſafety for ſuch a ſhrub how well rooted ſoever, to be planted under ſo tall a Cedar, that ſo it may not only in an hot ſeaſon (when tender Plants are apt to wither,) thence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſhade, but alſo in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſtormy weather, when there is no ſhelter. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, my Lord, what ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice your Lordſhip may do to that Countrey in this your tutelage to ſo good a deſign, that you may live long enough to experience, and by your (if need be) annual viſits to confirm, is the deſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>My Lord, Your Honours moſt humble Servant.</hi> W. Sympſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:33968:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is the uſefulneſs of things which renders them acceptable, and the benefit Mankind reaps from things applicable, makes them truly valuable, which as ſuch, really ought to gain opinion on their ſide, the common ſtandard of all matters relating to humane bodies; amongst which, thoſe that from their own nature are more nearly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed to the uſe of man, ought of right to purchaſe the moſt acceptance, the greateſt value and the beſt opinion.
<pb facs="tcp:33968:6"/>As to which, how nearly, deeply, and neceſſarily the health of man (the Prince of bodies) is concerned in the continuing or regaining thereof, let the healthful (who have lately known ſickneſs or the diſeaſed who now languiſh) ſpeak.</p>
            <p>Whatever therefore relates to the real curing or healing of Diſeaſes, and conſequently reſtoring of health, is truly valuable and ought to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe opinion (the common meaſure of things) on their ſide, and thence highly worth inquiring after, of which ſort are all Medical waters, and particularly thoſe of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> which how agreeable they are to the general conſtitution of humane bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? How congeneal to their fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? How great apperients or openers of obſtructions? How gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally they paſs? How frequently they remove the cauſes of Diſeaſes, and conſequently concur to the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of health, The inſtances of of Cures chiefly performed thereby
<pb facs="tcp:33968:7"/>(in the following Hiſtory ſet down) thoſe ſpeaking for others of the like nature, we have not an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to inſert) will (in order to the gaining the ends aforeſaid) yea ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorily and demonſtrably point out? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my late eſpouſing of <hi>Scarbrough</hi>-waters (the rational Induction whereto were the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inſtances, the main Subject of this Tract. I found it in the mouths of many perſons (with whom I or my friends converſed) that I was generally impeached of a retraction of what I had already writ. They apprehending as if my former Books were writ againſt the <hi>Spaw,</hi> which no perſon (who ever read them) can accuſe me of. For the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie was not taken up againſt the waters, as if deſigned to blemiſh them, but was grounded upon ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other manner of Ingredients then were believed, ſo that what I ſaid was not levelled againſt the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but urged againſt the depoſited
<pb facs="tcp:33968:7"/>principles or ingredients thereof. As to the truth of which I have a cloud of witneſſes, even all who have throughly read my two books of the <hi>Spaw,</hi> (the chief called <hi>Hydrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia Chymica.</hi> The latter <hi>Hydrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical</hi> Eſſayes) to whom I appeal, and particularly I adviſe ſuch as ſcruple thereat, for their further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to conſult <hi>p. 115, &amp;c.</hi> of my <hi>Hydrolog. Chym.</hi> where they will find what I aſcribe to the cure of the <hi>Scurvey, Dropſie, Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury, Jaundies, Melancholy, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Diſeaſes,</hi> &amp;c. If I was drawn a little aſide to have a jealous eye upon the waters (as ſome may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine from my <hi>Hydrolog.</hi> Eſſayes,) It was from an oblique credulity, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed by a dark <hi>Saturnine</hi> Influence, whoſe Clouds were ſoon diſperſed by the Sun-beams of experimental light, yea many were for a time (from the ſame male-influence) afraid of theſe waters, as if they had ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the mouth of the conſtellated
<pb facs="tcp:33968:8"/>Dogg above (animated by the riſing of a late <hi>Saturnal</hi> Star) as inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious at ſome hits of times, and in ſome ſenſe as the bitings of mad dogs here below, and were thence brought into a <hi>Hydrophoby, viz.</hi> was afraid of their proper remedy, by refuſing to approach the Medical waters; although they have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved a cure to theirs or other parallel Diſeaſes. And this Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>influence (in reference to theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) has (as I hinted) lately taken date from the Coſmical riſing of one of the <hi>Satilities,</hi> a churliſh Star of moroſe <hi>Saturn,</hi> which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the year <hi>1670, 1672.</hi> But if I have any skill in this ſort of Aſtrology, the effects of this unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate conſtellation, and dark vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaged <hi>Saturn,</hi> will, by calculation, be quite over in this year <hi>1679.</hi> and another more benign will begin to take place.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33968:8"/>
            <p>At this Pool, like that of <hi>Betheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah's</hi> (the dark miſts and foggs being blown over) are a multitude of <hi>Scorbuticks, Hypochondriacks</hi> and other <hi>Valetudinarians,</hi> (I mean ſuch as labour of the <hi>Scurvy, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, Stone,</hi> and other Diſeaſes) Male and Female in their ſeveral apartments, waiting for the moving of the waters, that thereby they may be healed of their reſpective Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, whilſt others (who come here chiefly for diverſion) only ſport in <hi>Neptunes</hi> Province, and like the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> only play with the waters. Were I to inſiſt upon an <hi>Encomium</hi> of theſe healing waters, I might venture, and that without Vanity) to ſpeak a bold word, <hi>viz.</hi> that if a Phyſician, who has theſe waters as a ſubſtitute, have but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a ſtock of ſome good ſpecificks, (without which he will often prove lame) to uſe upon occaſion, as neceſſity, through various indications ſhould require, might Eſſay to grapple al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb facs="tcp:33968:9"/>with any Diſeaſe, (if there be but any tolerable strength in nature) and ſcarce any would be able to stand before him; For thoſe waters do not work as vulgar waters, which as an <hi>Exotick</hi> ferment penetrates the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements, thins them, and by irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the <hi>Periſtaltick</hi> of the <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi> carries them away; But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, by the nimbleneſs and quickneſs of its Salts, inſinuates into the more inward receſſes of the obſtructed bowels, unbinding thoſe hidden <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatures,</hi> unhinging thoſe faſtned obſtacles, unbending thoſe inward strong ſprings in their <hi>elaſticity,</hi> whether in the juyces or ſolid parts of the body, unlocking thoſe ſhut-up bolts, and opening all thoſe hidden obſtructions which are far removed from the eye, or even intellectuals of many, and yet intimately, yea eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially concerned in the Fabrick of many <hi>Chronical</hi> Diſeaſes; which (as I ſaid) are with great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culity come at or reached, but with
<pb facs="tcp:33968:9"/>ſuch nimble agents and deeply pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Salts, as are the inmates of theſe waters. Amongſt which, that of <hi>Nitre</hi> is ſo exquiſitely (by the Chymiſtry of nature) mixed, and contempered with the <hi>Alluminous</hi> Salt, as that water is thereby (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other excellent waters) ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the most effectual quencher of thirst of any water that ever I ſaw, yea perhaps I might not be much miſtaken, if I ſhould ſay that the temperature of the <hi>Mineral</hi> juyces performed by the wonderful ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raneal induſtry (I had well nigh ſaid <hi>Chymiſtry</hi>) of Nature, are ſuch as if in reference to quenching (yea and peradventure alſo as to other vertues) it may (and that without vanity) be reputed one of the beſt of the known healing waters in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have studied conciſeneſs, and yet are larger in the main than we expected. I could not well be more compendious, eſpecially when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered,
<pb facs="tcp:33968:10"/>how I was under an obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to give the Readers (chiefly the more ingenious ſort) ſome tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſatisfaction, at leaſt in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſome <hi>Phenomina</hi> neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to be inſiſted on, in a diſcourſe of this nature.—This is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, theſe waters being carried at a distance, are found to operate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing nigh ſo well, as to the cure of Diſeaſes, as when drunk at the Spring-head.</p>
            <p>To conſider, what faithfulneſs I have uſed in putting down the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Caſes? What care I have taken in methodically ranging them under their particular heads? And as near as I could in reducing them to their diſtinct claſses, and in all with what candour to truth I have uſed either in tranſcribing, or origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally placing down the various To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks of the following Hiſtory, I refer to every unbyaſſed Reader by his beſt Inqueſt to determine and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf? where we do not rank
<pb facs="tcp:33968:10"/>Patients in their ſeveral claſſes firſt or laſt, according to the dignity of the perſons, ſo much as according to the eminency of their reſpective caſes. Amongſt whom, thoſe who are ſo publick-minded as to permit their names to atteſt their cures, thereby do (as of right they ought) Juſtice to the waters, Service to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and mean-while, no injury to themſelves. Thus wiſhing them, who may be concerned, much good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs by the due, proper, and advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable uſe of the waters,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I remain Thine further to ſerve Thee,</hi> W. Simpſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33968:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33968:11"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF <hi>Scarbrough-Spaw.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Diſeaſes we propoſe to treat of, and to which the uſe of the waters are moſt proper, are cheifly Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, or ſuch whoſe cauſes are ſo rooted as to continue long unleſs cured by proper Remedies: amongſt which, the moſt graſſant or moſt univerſally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting, are, firſt the Scurvie with its branchings, complications and inocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations into other diſeaſes: next the Flatus Hypochondriacus, or diſeaſes ſpringing from Melancholy. 3. the Stone and Strangury. 4. Agues. 5. The Jaundies. 6. The Dropſice. 7. Wormes. 8. Womens diſeaſes, &amp;c. next to which we but touch upon acute diſeaſes.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:33968:12"/>
            <p>We ſhall begin with the Scurvy, which, with its appendices, is the moſt ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Malady, No Cities, towns, villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, free from it, nay ſcarce any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily which is not notorious for ſome one or other perſons therein afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more or leſs with the Symptoms thereof.</p>
            <p>It is not now our intended work here to give the definition and various di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions or ſpecifications of the Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, only in ſhort ſhall crave leave to ſay that it depends cheifly, if not ſolely, upon the depraved ferments, and viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated digeſtions of the body, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly and primarily of the Stomack: (that <hi>Primum mobile</hi> of this and other chronical diſeaſes) where reſides the very ſeminary of the ſcorbutick fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, conſiſting chiefly in a ſpurious Acidity, which vitiating the ſubſequent digeſtions (ſome more then others ſpreds it ſelf by degrees into the blood and other juices, until it appear in all its colours, and branched fort in all its ſymptoms and products.</p>
            <p>The ſymptoms of the Scurvy are various, ſometimes under one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe ſometimes under another, they are frequently of theſe ſorts (b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33968:12"/>ſome of which that diſeaſe diſcovers it ſelf) viz. an univerſal laſſitude and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the knees, dulneſs or heavineſs of ſpirits, erratick pains, ſhortneſs of breath, tumors, ulcers of many ſorts, ſpots and blotches upon the legs, rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the skin, and other impurities of the outward parts, diſcolourdeneſs, and ſoreneſs of gums, pain and looſeneſs in the teeth, ſour ſtink of breath, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As to a further diſquiſition into the nature and cauſes of the Scurvy, how the foundation thereof is laid in the depravation of the ferment of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, and how the firſt Errour, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing corrected in the ſubſequent digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but carried into the blood, ſubverting the craſis thereof, alters the ſweet balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick ſoft natural temper thereof into an auſtere, ſour, ſaltineſs, perverting its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and genuine fermentation, and how the blood corrupted by the vitiating fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Scurvy, breaths forth impure ſtreams, which making their Egreſs through the pores of the outward parts, are (by obſtructions they find there) coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated upon the outward parts, and ſo make ſpots, blotches, foulneſs, ſcurf, roughneſs (as if netled) and other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities of the skin, the uſual effects of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33968:13"/>that diſeaſe: and how the difference in Scurvys, are chiefly aſcribable to varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Acids or ſome acrimonious fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prevailing in the juices of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; And how by analogy, the skin is compared to a tranſparent glaſs, upon which the ſtreams ariſing from that ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fermentation of the blood and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, being too groſs to be pervious to the pores thereof, might well be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to condenſe along the ſides, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting ſpots, ſtains, foul damps, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to thoſe impure miſts, and dark ſteams, really ariſing from the baſtardly fermentation of the blood in Scurvies, and condenſed upon the external parts, &amp;c. To a further diſquiſition, I ſay, of all which, we refer the reader to what wee have ſaid thereon in our <hi>Hydrolog. Chymic.</hi> p. 70. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhall immediately come to the matter we chiefly aime at viz the Enumeration of perticular cure of the Scurvy and its branches of complications performed by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33968:13"/>
               <head>Cures of the Scurvy by the Waters.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Firſt ſhall be Major <hi>Taylors</hi> Caſe.</head>
               <p>IN the year 50 or 51 he had a long lingering ſcorbutick and complicated Malady, had a dry Cough, ſhort-winded, had no appetite or digeſtion could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eat, Sleep, nor capable of any Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, was brought by impoveriſhment of Spirit, very low, and lean, even to a great debilitude; in which languiſhing conditition he continued notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the help the Phyſicians could make him; who by them was adjuged conſumptive, and by them and on all hands concluded a dying-man: was however reſolved for <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome noiſe of its vertues, for he thus thought, that ſeeing he was a man already under the ſentence of death, he muſt dye if he ſtayed at home, it was but dying and it could be no worſe at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> or elſ-where, and as to the place he was not ſolicitous; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon contrary to advice, undertakes the journey, although with very great difficulty, becauſe of his great weakneſs, he was told to his great diſcouragement,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33968:14"/>that he ſhould never return alive: (if ſo he reſolved to be buried at <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi>) he drank the waters three days before it began to work, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that time no Phyſician by to adviſe with: Then he filled himſelf very full with the waters, taking about five pints thereof: upon which it made him very ſick, gave him onely one vomit, and ſo wrought downward; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in about a weeks time, he began to find benefit, and in about fourteen days after (drinking every day the waters) he found himſelf ſo much altered for the better, as all the bad Symptoms gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually went off, the waters paſſed well, working throughly upon the humors, diſcharging the peccant matter, correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scorbutick acid ferment, opening obſtructions, dulcified the blood, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened the weakned tone of the Stomack and bowels, proured an appetite, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the digeſtion, brought on reſt, as the genuine reſult of the former, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came cheerfull, returned home (contrary to the expectation of all) very well, not in a litter, but on horſe-back, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering ſtrength daily. Then he thought himſelf ſo well as he needed not come next year, nor did he: But finding
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33968:14"/>himſelf afterwards not well, came the next year after: And ſo continued till 64 intermitting one in 3 or 4 years, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time he had his health as well as he would wiſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Major <hi>Taylor's</hi> caſe of the Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy cured a ſecond time by the Waters.</head>
               <p n="2">2. DUring the time of his being abroad at <hi>Tangier,</hi> which was about five years, at his return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> he found himſelf in as bad a ſtate of health as he was at his firſt coming to the waters aforeſaid. The Scorbutick Symptoms prevailing ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon him, his legs, (as an addition and product of this ſort of Scurvy) was covered over with white ſcales, and he, in the main, over-run with the Scurvy from the Sea-air, with moſt of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications thereof aforeſaid, betakes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his former Aſylum for releif and help, drank the waters twice that Summer (in the year 70) found as conſiderable an Event, yea as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by the waters as before, taking off the Symptoms of the Scurvy as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated with other weakneſs, purified
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33968:15"/>the blood, and thereby made the ſcales fall off: So continued drinking the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters every year ſince except one, and injoys his health very well, was at <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brouogh</hi> twice laſt Summer, being the latter time there with my Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>My Lady <hi>Carey</hi> her caſe.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Third cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p n="3">3 JUly 5th 77 ſhe was highly Scorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, the firſt remarkable appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance whereof was a ſtitch ſhe had in her right breſt, which like a dart ſtruck through to her back: That a ſtrong Scorbutick Acidum prevailed in her Stomack, was evident, in that when ſhe took new milk, it preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came curdled into cheeſe, which ſhe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited up (with great difficulty and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuffocation,) in the very form of a cheeſe curd, as if indeed the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick Acid was the runnet which made cheeſe of milk while in the Stomack: ſhe took ſome Tobacco which cauſed more of the ſame cheeſy congulum come up: after which this Scorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Acidum was in great part carried
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33968:15"/>upon the nerves, whence ſhe fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an univerſal trembling or paraly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick fit, ſo as every part of her trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, which continued about half an hour, during which time ſhe could not ſpeak, and (as an argument of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied convulſive motion) her mouth was drawn a little aſide; but as to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidneſs of colour and other dangerous Symptoms, ſhe ſeemed well nigh Expire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Then was the ſcene of this Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick ferment transfered into the blood, where it cauſed ſuch a ſpurious fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, as thereupon a violent heat was contracted, which continued (as if ſhe had been in a feaver) for four dayes, which with ſweating Medicines was part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſpired, and partly carried or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the urinary veſſels, where the Scurvy Acid (thus variouſly diſguiſed) at length chiefly fixt, and acted ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of Scene, bringing on the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury or ſtoppage of Urine, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued day and night (not paſt two ſpoonfuls a time) and her water con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly mixed with blood, and that for 14 weeks together: mean while ſome of the Scorbutick Acidum lodged in the Stomack, depraving the ferment thereof, whence the loſt her appetite: and part
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33968:16"/>of it was ſent or precipitated from the blood in its circulation upon the lungs, whence from the obſtructing Acidum they were ſtuffed and had not (through a leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Syſtole and Diaſtole) a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, the cauſe of her ſhort winded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and from both was brought on a decaying of Spirits and ſtrength, and an impoveriſhment of her body, together with a great pain in the urinary Veſſels.</p>
               <p>Thus the Scurvy had appeared under various maſques, as if indeed it had been a complication of many other maladies, <hi>viz.</hi> a baſtard Pluriſie, Surfet, Palſy, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, Fever, Strangury, Stone, (with the aggravation of mixt blood) <hi>dolor Nephriticus, Apepſie, Aſthma, Maraſmus,</hi> while really (as may be concluded from the range of Symptoms emerging from the frequent <hi>metaſtaſis</hi> of the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick Acid) they were but various ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, and different guiſes the ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick ferment had put on, as it was lodged in, or transferred from one part, organ, or juice to another: was all (I ſay) but the Scurvy under diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent maſques.</p>
               <p>This worthy Lady, under the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the aforeſaid Symptoms,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33968:16"/>(ſomewhat alleviated) by which ſhe had been under confinement to her Chamber for eight months, by advice, at length betakes her ſelf to <hi>Scarbrough-Spaw, May</hi> 28, drank the waters, and found immediate help; For the Scorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Symptoms abated, her appetite was recruited, and ſtrength regained: And although the waters did not paſs by U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine (the obſtructions being ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate) at the firſt time of drinking thereof, which was onely for 10 days: yet upon her Ladyſhips return again to the waters; they then made their way through thoſe formerly obſtructed paſſages, took off all bad Symptoms, formerly afflicting thoſe parts, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting her pain, procured a good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, brought on (conſidering her age) a good Athletick habit of body; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came very active cheerfull and healthfull, and as if renewed again in her old age, the good effects thereof continued: for I waited on her near two months after her returne from the water and found her well as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33968:17"/>
               <head>A Fourth cure.</head>
               <p n="4">4 THe Right Honorable <hi>James</hi> Earl of <hi>Suffolk</hi> had been for the ſpace of thirteen years trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a moſt grievous Scorbutick pain (for ſo it appeared by the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms) at the Stomack, which uſually ſeized on him at meals, eſpecially if he did eat fleſh, ſo as was forced to give over, though ſometimes at two or three bits of meat, and thus it would hold him for ſeveral hours, cauſing a great diſtention and hardneſs upon the region of the Stomack, with torſions on the right ſide, ſo as it made his very ribs on that ſide to bend: whoſe beſt eaſe was to ſit low, and thruſt his thumb with all his force upon his Stomack. His Lordſhip had ſought for cure both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Phyſicians he could hear of, but found none, the malady reſiſting all means that could be uſed: His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip came to theſe waters, and drank a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three weeks, after a few days (as Dr. <hi>Whittie,</hi> who was then at the <hi>Spaw</hi> and attended him, obſerved) the fits
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33968:17"/>leſſened by degrees, that he could better Eat, and concoct his meat with little pain: who gave his Lordſhip ſome grounds of hope, that after he was ſettled at home from the waters and his Journey, he might find a perfect recovery, which through the mercy of God did accordingly ſucceed, ſo as he has ſcarce any footſteps of his former malady, but can eat any ſort of meat without pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fifth is Sir <hi>John Anderſon's</hi> Caſe given in a letter under his own hand to Dr. <hi>Whittie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIr, upon your requeſt to give you an account of the effects of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough-Spaw,</hi> I preſent you with this, as a true narrative of what I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. In <hi>Anno</hi> 1661 finding my ſelf very much inclining to the Scurvy (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving moſt of the Symptoms attending that diſeaſe) I came to <hi>Scarbrough;</hi> and muſt confeſs, that after a fortnights drinking of the waters, I found both the pains of my knees and ſhort wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs wholly gone, and thoſe other impediments which are concomitants of that diſtemper: being thus encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, at the convenient time of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33968:18"/>next year I repaired thither again, and very unexpectedly I was there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a fit of the Gout, under which malady I had formerly ſuffered, but after I had drank the waters about a week I was freed from all my pain, and I thank God (excepting ſome ſmall remembrances, as heat in that joint of my toe) I never had ſince any thing of pain worth taking notice of. In 1663. I found my blood extreamly hot, and ſuch pricking in my hands and feet, and continual bleeding at the noſe, that I feared an extraordinary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, which after uſing of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I was clearly freed from. In the year 1664 I was prevented by extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary occaſions and could not come to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> and moſt part of that Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the ſucceeding Spring I was much afflicted with an extraordinary heat in my bowels, and ſhort-winded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and pain in my knees, which by the bleſſing of God, and the goodneſs of the waters, joined with your advice and aſſiſtance in uſing them, I find my ſelf quitted of. And this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation I have made this year of my own uſing them, that after I had drank three days (the waters having
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33968:18"/>fully anſwered my expectation in all particulars) I reſolved one night to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf with a very ſlender Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and the next morning I obſerv'd that I made plentifull ſtore of Urine, as uſually before I drank the waters, after which I drank four quarts of water, and reſolved to faſt untill they had fully compleated their operation which (as I conceive) ended about three in the afternoon; I ſtill kept faſting to ſee if they would work longer, which in ſome ſmall meaſure they did till five, but more by Urine then ſiege, after which, I meaſured the quantity that had come from me, in which I was as exact as I was in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the water it ſelf, and when I had compared what had paſſed through, with the quantity that I drank, I found the 4 quarts increaſed to five and very near a pint, which could not be increaſed by any thing I took, for untill five I had faſted from all things and then took but a gill of Wormwood wine, which was all that could help to make the addition, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the humors of the body which were plentifully caſt out with the waters. This from <hi>Sir your very affectionate Friend</hi> John Anderſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33968:19"/>
               <head>The Sixth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> of <hi>Hull</hi> had a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with an aguiſh intervall, being a fever ſpun out at length by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxyſms, and thence upon the <hi>exit</hi> thereof, had contracted a Scorbutick A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pepſie and chachectical habit of body (as the relict of his late Quartan) having much pains and weakneſs in his joints all over him, ſo as he could ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walk, and his appetite to food was taken away: by advice, he came to the waters of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> drank them, and found himſelf better in a few days. After eight or ten days drinking, he got an Excellent good Stomack, and in about fourteen days time, his Scorbutick Symptoms went off, and he returned as well in health home as he had been of twenty years before, as I had from his own mouth: upon which account he yearly drinks the waters with good ſucceſs ever ſince, which is now ſeaven or eight years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33968:19"/>
               <head>A Seventh cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANne Robinſon</hi> laboured under a Scorbutick ferment vitiating the natural ferment of the Stomack, which took away her appetite, and procured a great weakneſs and languor of body, her diſeaſe was chronical, of long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, held her above two years: in order to the cure of which, ſhe had taken vomits and other medicaments according to the advice of ſome Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians but all in vain, ſhe ſtill become<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worſe and worſe, in ſo much as ſhe was judged conſumptive, ſhe (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the advice of one Phyſician ſhe had conſulted) applies her ſelf to the waters, drank them for fourteen days, and that without any ſucceſs at all, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued as bad as at firſt: at length when fourteen days were expired, ſhe began to expectorate, or ſpit abundance of Phlegm which in the aforeſaid time had been looſned: whereupon ſhe grew better, got a Stomack to her food, regained ſtrength, ſo as in a months time (after the firſt drinking) ſhe found her ſelf very well: And retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned home in good health. But after a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33968:20"/>while at home, ſhe began again in the ſame malady: whereupon ſhe came again the next <hi>Spaw</hi> time, and was cured a ſecond time: alſo ſhe had ſome touches of her former Symptoms a third time, but after her third drinking, ſhe was throughly well recovered, and ſo continued ever ſince, being now ſeveral years ago: which account I had from her own mouth at the Waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Eighth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>J. <hi>C.</hi> near <hi>York,</hi> laboured under a Scorbutick diſorder of his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, evident by its great oppreſſion by Phlegm, and water, ſo as every morning he had great and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome boknings or retchings to vomit, whereby a clear water came off, and after that, by much ſtrugglings, came up Phlegm, and then he was at ſome eaſe, during which time it took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his appetite: This continued, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the advice of an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Phyſician, who at length ordered him to come to theſe waters, where he found great relief, it thinns his Phlegm and carryes it off by ſeidge, and diſpoſeth ſo of the clear water, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33968:20"/>uſed to diſtill <hi>per lingulam</hi> from his Stomack, as he is well, and continues ſo for many months after drinking the waters, till towards the Spring, and then it begins again, and continues till he comes to the waters, which takes it away again, and he returns well home. Upon which action he every year fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents the waters and that with good ſucceſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Ninth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Chriſtopher Adams</hi> of <hi>Camelſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field Yorkshire,</hi> aged ſeventy three years, had for ſix years together been miſerably tormented with pain in his leggs, feebleneſs in his knees, frequent faintings, and a dry Itch over all his skin, he had advice with ſeveral Phyſicians, who had ordered him Diet-drinks, Diaphoreticks, Oyntments, &amp;c. But without any ſucceſs at all, he came at length to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and upon drinking thoſe waters he found per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect eaſe in all the aforeſaid Symptoms; he had alſo been ſore afflicted with diz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zineſs in his head and loſs of memory, his undeſtanding alſo was ſometimes ſo clouded, that he could not diſcern
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33968:21"/>the quarters of heaven, or know the Eaſt from the Weſt, and ſometimes was wont to fall: by the uſe of the <hi>Spaw,</hi> he recovered out of the ſaid Symptoms, and never had any fits ſince conſiderable. For prevention whereof he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his annual viſits at <hi>Scarbrough</hi> for ſeven years, although he lived at 40 miles diſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Tenth caſe</head>
               <p>MAdam <hi>Pockley</hi> nere <hi>Selby</hi> in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> had a bad Stomack, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with an ill digeſtion, a great flatulency or windy-riftings: ſhe drank the waters laſt year near fourteen days, with ſome intervall, which procured her a very good Stomack to her meat, ſo as ſhe ſaid, ſhe eat near as much meat, and that with ſavourineſs and good reliſh, in one day at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> as in a week at home: her meat alſo digeſting well, and the windineſs (the fruit of Indigeſtion) was gone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33968:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>1</hi> Scorbutick Cholera.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Tenth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>SIr <hi>W. Ker,</hi> upon the borders of <hi>Scotland</hi> (a worthy Knight) la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured under a Scorbutick <hi>Cholera,</hi> with a great oppreſſion of wind upon his Stomack: in ſo much as he could ſcarce get any meat down, but was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently heaved up by the force and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the wind, and what ever he eat at night, he was ſure after his firſt ſleep to be deſperate ſick there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, till it was carryed off both by vomiting and purging: whereby was brought on a great debilitude of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, could ſcarce digeſt any meat, and was thence reduced to a very weak ſtate of body, being brought to a great enfeeblement by the prevalency of the aforeſaid Scorbutick Symptoms: have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had much advice before, and had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken much Phyſick but to little purpoſe, was adviſed by his Phyſician Dr. <hi>Simpſon</hi> (an Eminent Phyſician in <hi>Scotland</hi>) to apply himſelf to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> waters: who accordingly did, and upon five or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33968:22"/>ſix days drinking thereof, according to advice, found himſelf much better, and the Symptoms abating, could take food, and had a pretty good digeſtion, the <hi>flatus</hi> ceaſing; and in about ten or twelve days time, he returned home as well in health as ever he had been before, which happened in the year 74; found ſo much good by drinking the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as he has come every year ſince, and ſo intends to do for the future if he lives: from whoſe own mouth I had the aforeſaid relation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>
                  <hi>2</hi> Scorbutick Cholera.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Eleventh cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>G.— laboured under a Scorbutick Apepſie, and indigeſtion, throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ſometimes a matter of a greaſy form, ſo as might be made into balls, other while caſting up that little food he took, raw and indigeſted, many hours after taking thereof, being unaltered in its form, from what it was when taken, being contracted by a ſurfeit from cold, by which Symptoms he became weak in body and unfit for labour: he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33968:22"/>thus for above two years, moſt what ſick after taking any food, and what he took was ſo little as by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation was ſcarce able to ſuſtain him: he came to the waters, drank them four dayes, each day twelve pints, which wrought very plentifully with him: The very firſt day, he began to eat with an appetite, what food he took ſtaied with him, and in the compaſs of the foreſaid time, he got a very good Stomack to his meat, which alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted very well, and he thereupon reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. The waters during their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (eſpecially the laſt day) made him very ſore behind, which was a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraion <hi>a poſteriori</hi> of the efficacy of the waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>
                  <hi>3</hi> Scorbutick Cholera.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Twelfth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>A Scotch Gentleman was afflicted with a Scorbutick indigeſtion and <hi>flatus</hi> upon his Stomack, ſo as what ever he took he threw it up preſently after; This continued for about three quarters of a year, he came (in order
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33968:23"/>to his help) to drink the <hi>Scarbrough</hi> waters, the firſt week he found no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit at all: But being put upon a more regular Method of taking them: he then, the firſt day after, began to take ſome broth, which ſtaid with him, next day he could take and digeſt a little meat, which ſtaied, and agreed well with him: and in a few days after had a very good Stomack, digeſted his meat very well, and returned home in health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>
                  <hi>4</hi> Scorbutick Cholera.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Thirteenth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>A Noble Lord contracted a diſorde upon his Stomack by eating Fiſh (and that of ſuch ſort, which would the ſooneſt, for want of digeſtion grow putrid upon the ſtomack) and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by drinking upon it ſome bad wines: from which indigeſtion his Lordſhip was much put out of order: I adviſed him to drink the waters, which while he was doing, ſends for me all in haſt, when I came, he told me he was ill at his Stomack, had a pain
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33968:23"/>and dizzineſs in his head, I adviſed his Lordſhip to follow it yet, by taking more water, which he did, and preſently while I ſtaied by him, he began to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit abundance of tough Phlegm, and yellow bitter choller, which clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Stomach, and carried the reſt downwards; ſo he was preſently at eaſe, nature by the help of the waters diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging her ſelf both wayes of what was burdenſome; whence, the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his Stomack, pain, and dizzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his head, went forthwith away, and by drinking the waters ſome few days, he got a good Stomach to his meat, alſo a freſh lively colour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fourteenth cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Humfrey Birch</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> had been long troubled with loſs of appetite and debility of concoction, the ferment of his Stomach being ſo viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and the tone of the membranes thereof ſo altered as that he did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly caſt up his meat, (which were undoubted Symptoms of the Scurvy as it had ſeated it ſelf in the Stomach) This being the ſecond year of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> he acknowledged
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33968:24"/>he had found a perfect cure, being able to eat and concoct any ſort of meat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fitfteenth cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Roger Maynat</hi> of <hi>Dalton-Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> laboured for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three years together under the ſame malady, which had exceedingly abated his ſtrength, and reſiſted all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of Phyſicians: who was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured after one weeks drinking of the waters, and for prevention has not failed for ſeveral years to viſit them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Sixteenth cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>William Linſtead</hi> of <hi>Hull</hi> had got a Scorbutick ſurfeit, which brought on an exceſſive vomiting and purging even to fourſcore times: all his body over he broke out into red pimples, as if it had been the ſmall pox; upon his drinking of the waters, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the Symptoms abated, and his ſtrength and ſtomach encreaſed daily, and in four or five days was reſtored to perfect health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33968:24"/>
               <head>The Seventeenth cure, <hi>viz.</hi> a Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick Heart-burn.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAtthew Alured</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> of <hi>Bever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> in <hi>Yorkshire</hi> was many years ſore afflicted with a Scorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Heart-burn, which tormented him day and night notwithſtanding much means uſed for cure, found benefit here, on which account he yearly fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented them.</p>
               <p>I reckon the ſeven laſt caſes of Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick Cholar's, together with that of the Scorbutick heart-burn as moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly reducible to the Claſſis of the Scurvy, putting them under that head, as (for Method ſake) moſt adapted thereto, although the concurring cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances doth not only in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect quadrate therewith; however I was biaſſed thereto, not only (as I ſaid) for Method ſake but alſo as led by this reaſon, that if the Scorbutick ferment had ſetled or fixt it ſelf in ſome other parts, organs, or juyces of the bodyes of thoſe aforeſaid patients, it would then doubtleſs have put on other Symptoms, and appeared under ſuch dreſſes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33968:25"/>as it might eaſily enough have been diſcovered (even by a vulgar Eye) to be no other than the Scurvy.</p>
               <p>Now come we to another branch or ſpecies of the Scurvy, as its ferment fixeth it ſelf in other parts, <hi>viz.</hi> either the lungs or Inteſtines or ſmaller guts; where it acts another ſcene of Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms. The firſt of which we call a Scorbutick <hi>Aſthma,</hi> becauſe the ferment of the Scurvy ſeems chiefly to fix it ſelf upon the Lungs, on which parts chiefly the tragedy of Scorbutick Symptoms are acted, of which take one Caſe and Cure as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Eighteenth cure.</head>
               <p>MRs. <hi>Mary Byron</hi> of <hi>Koosby</hi> in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> had been three or four years exceedingly troubled with a ſtopping at her breaſt, in ſo much as for a month or five weeks together ſometimes ſhe could not lye down in her bed but was bolſtered up with pillows, ſhe was brought alſo to that exceſſive weakneſs, that ſhe could ſcarce go over the houſe when ſhe was at the beſt, and her fleſh was quite conſumed, being almoſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but skin and bone; ſhe could never eat any thing, but caſt it up
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33968:25"/>againe with coughing, nor could ſhe drink at any time, but preſently ſhe was ſcarce able to ſpeak for want of breath, the came to theſe waters and drank about eight or ten days, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning home with perfect health, and has ſo continued, ſince when ſhe hath had a child.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, we for diſtinction ſake, call Scorbutick Collicks: which, that they are indeed Collicks, is evident from the Symptoms immediately emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging therefrom; and next that they are Scorbutick, is as apparent, becauſe they take as deep rooting, as the very ferment of the Scurvy, are as durable, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to vulgar Methods, and cured moſtly with ſuch Antiſcorbuticks, as reſpect the deep roots of ſuch fixt diſeaſes, under which as ſtems thereof, or ſpecies of Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick Collicks, we compriſe alſo ſome Diarrhea's or looſneſſes, the Gripes and Dyſenteries or Bloody fluxes: all which have not always their ſource or firſt ſpring from the Inteſtines, but many times from a Symbolical Scorbutick Acid, as ſometimes tranſmitted thither from the blood co-operating in the Stomach: yet for method and diſtinction ſake we reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:33968:26"/>
               <head>Scorbutick Cholick.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Ninteenth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>A Man (living in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham</hi>) laboured under a grievous Scorbutick Collick, aſſlicting his body, eſpecially below his navel, with great pain, his ſtomach was gone, had exceſſive pains all over him, was brought exceeding weak as he could ſcarce walk: came to drink the waters, which he did with ſo great ſucceſs as his Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick pains abated and gradually went away, got a good Stomach and digeſted his meat well: And in about eight days time, was ſo well recovered, as to the aſtoniſhment of his wife, and freinds he could run, and leap upon the ſands.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick-Stone-Collick.</head>
               <head type="sub">The twentieth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Hall</hi> near <hi>Hallifax</hi> in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> was under Dr. <hi>Wharton</hi> and Dr. <hi>Paget</hi> (two eminent Phyſicians)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33968:26"/>hands in <hi>London,</hi> for a complication of an Ague and Stone-Collick, which wrought up to his Stomach and made him very ſick; I add Scorbutick, becauſe Agues (not well cured) frequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into Scorbutick habits of body, which alſo fixing upon the urinary paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is the patron of many tormenting evils: had many medicines eſpecially pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, preſcribed, which never paſſed with him: At length, after he came into the Country, he voided ſeveral ſtones: Then came to drink the waters at <hi>Knars<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> but finding thoſe not to paſs with him, came to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and tryed thoſe waters, which he fonnd to paſs exceeding well, above all the purging medicines he had ever taken, onely for the firſt two or three days made him very ſore in his poſteriors, but carried off the Scorbutick Chollick, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licts of his Ague, procuring a very good Stomach, which before was very bad and weak: he received ſo much good thereby, as he has now by times frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe waters for ten years: he had one fit of his Chollick this laſt Summer at the <hi>Spaw,</hi> but upon drinking of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, it preſently went off: he obſerved, that for ſome few days it wrought like
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33968:27"/>
                  <hi>Epſom</hi> or <hi>Barnet,</hi> moſtly by ſeidge, but more effectually than either of them: and other days it wrought like <hi>Tunbridge</hi> or <hi>Knarsbrough,</hi> chiefly by Urine.</p>
               <p>This laſt Inſtance alſo relates to the Claſſis of the Stone cures, but that the Symptoms thereof doth chiefly and ſtrongly bear upon the Scorbutick fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the cauſe why we rank it under this head of the Scurvy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick Diarrhea or looſneſs.</head>
               <head type="sub">The One and twentieth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>P. <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> his wife, was troubled with an exceſſive looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, drank the waters, which after purging, preſently ſtayed her looſneſs, and ſhe was well: yea as often as ſhe has any trouble that way, applyes her ſelf to the waters, whether in Summer or Winter, by which ſhe alwayes finds good ſucceſs; it commonly cures her with one days drinking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33968:27"/>
               <head>Scorbutick Gripes.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Two and twentieth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>P. <hi>B.</hi> a Maſter of a ſhip at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> (my late patient) was afflicted with the Gripes, ſo as he could neither ſit, ſtand, nor go without great torments; drank the waters, which at firſt he vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, but by a peculiar way or method of taking the waters, giving him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what which made them find the way through, opening the paſſages, dinted the acrimony or acidity impacted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Guts, quieted the pain, and took away all bad Symptoms, ſo he recovered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick Dyſentery or Bloody-flux.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Three and twntieth cure of the Scurvy.</head>
               <p>THE aforeſaid Maſter of a ſhips brother in law, was afflicted with a Dyſentery or Bloody-flux, ſo as he was not in a capacity (being a Sea-man) of going aboard his Veſſel, he was weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33968:28"/>thereby and brought very low: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter trying in vain what other advice he could get, drank the waters, and in a few days the bad Symptoms were off, and he was perfectly cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The twenty fourth Cure.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SIlveſter Sympſon</hi> of <hi>Driffield</hi> in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> had a bloody-flux eight years ſo as he all that ſpace was forced to riſe to ſtoole every night three or four times. It had reſiſted all other means he had attempted. He went to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and was cured perfectly in two or three days with the waters alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick piſſing of blood.</head>
               <head type="sub">The twenty fifth Cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Chapman</hi> of 80 years of age was much and often troubled with piſſing blood, wherupon he made his recourſe to <hi>Scarbrough's-Spaw,</hi> which took away that threatning Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome by giving him preſent Eaſe, which was publickly known among the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood at <hi>Hacknes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33968:28"/>
               <p>Now we come to reckon upon ſome other ſpecificated Scurveys, in whoſe cauſes and Symptoms the Scurvy is chiefly twiſted <hi>viz.</hi> Scorbutick-Rheuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, Eriſipela's, Ulcers, Elephantiaſis, and Leprous Scurvy, and ſhall give a ſingle inſtance of cure of each by the waters, at leaſt by their chief help, as follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick Rheumatiſme.</head>
               <head type="sub">The twenty ſixth Cure.</head>
               <p>A. <hi>W.</hi> of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> was troubled with a Scorbutick Rheumatiſme, which cheifly afflicted her right arm and ſhoulder, with grievous and almoſt inſufferable pain; ſo as (through great extremity) ſhe cryed forth I ordered her (being ſomewhat in years) a veſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory plaiſter to be applied to her ſhoulder on the ſame ſide, and a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation made <hi>Ex fol. Ebuli, Salv. agreſt. Et fl. Sambuci</hi> ā ā boyled in Sea-water: then I adviſed her ſome pills with the waters, whereby they wrought well: and the had eaſe in the worſt of her paroxyſme by the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33968:29"/>night Julep <hi>(viz) Aq. papav. Rhead.</hi> ℥<hi>iiij vel</hi> ℥<hi>iiij Syr. Limon.</hi> ℥<hi>i ſs, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>
                     <hi rend="sup">u</hi> C li. acidulat.</hi> which ſhe took for three or four nights with great ſucceſs and advantage, cauſing her to reſt well: So ſhe recovered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>A Scorbutick Cattarrhe.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Seven and twentieth cure.</head>
               <p>MRs. <hi>Mary Bateman</hi> of <hi>York</hi> had been much troubled with Rheumes, which had ſwelled up her face and eyes, and reſiſted all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, found very much benefit by the uſe of this water, more then all other methods that had been preſcribed for her, upon account whereof ſhe has been an annuall viſiter of it theſe twelve years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick Eriſipela's.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Eight and twentieth cure.</head>
               <p>THE daughter of the aforeſaid woman (of about ten years of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33968:29"/>age or more, had an Eriſipelas or Infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in her legg, called vulgarly the ſhingles or St. <hi>Anthony's</hi> fire, which began the Winter before; It of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ran with a lee, ſo as the cloth ſhe wrapt it with would cleave and be baked thereto, and was very painfull to her (even to make her cry) at every taking off, ſhe had a poultiſs laid on, which was hard baked thereto, which I ordered them to take off, and throw away: I adviſed her to drink the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with a few pils, and ordered her a Topick of Venice Treacle, one ounce mixt in a pint of the beſt White-Wine, bathing it ſeveral times a day there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, leaving a double linnen cloth dipt therein upon her legg: whereby in a few days time her leg grew better, the Inflamation abated, and the pain was mitigated: So that in leſs than a months time the bad Symptoms went quite off, and her leg was perfectly whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Nine and twentieth cure.</head>
               <p>A Gentleman at the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> (Mr. <hi>K.</hi>) now not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33968:30"/>far off <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> had a Scrobutick Ulcer in both feet croſs the toes (while in the Colledge) which brought him much pain, the ſore was white and moſt-what wept forth a Lee, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a Scorbutick Acidum, the chief cauſe of pain: He laboured under the grief hereof for about two years, notwithſtanding all the help a <hi>Cantabrigian</hi> Phyſician could make him; he came upon an occaſion into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and drank the waters of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> for ten days: (being mindfull to try, if he could thence get any help.) The operation of the waters was ſuch, as brought away a matter as black as pitch: whereupon the former inveterate and obſtinate Symptoms (that would not bend to Phyſick nor outward Topicks before) now abated: his pain went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the Scorbutick Lee was dryed up, (its Acidum being corrected in the blood by the waters,) and the Ulcers healed, was thereupon cured: being encouraged hereby, frequents the waters every year ſince, (he was cured in the year 1655.) only miſſed coming one year, during which interval or intermiſſion, he had a dangerous Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which was about ſeven or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33968:30"/>eight years ago; ſince which he has had his health well: Which account I had from his own mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick Elephantiaſis.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Thirtieth cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Rogers</hi>'s daughter of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> had a Scorbutick <hi>Elephantiaſis</hi> almoſt all over her: which alſo, from the Scorbutick Acidum ſeiſing the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons and ligaments of her joints, had rendred her well nigh decrepid: ſhe drank the waters, and in about a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nights time or more, the blood was ſo purified, as it caſt off thoſe externall feculencies or recrements of the ultimate digeſtion in the form of white ſcales, and ſo ſweetned the blood and latex, and opened obſtructions, as that it removed thoſe bolts and hedges which were faſtned upon the joynts and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments, and begot a healthfull habit of body: So her skin became clear and ſmooth, and ſhe well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:33968:31"/>
               <head>Leprous Scurvy.</head>
               <head type="sub">The One and thirtieth cure.</head>
               <p>A Boy had a leprous Scurvy, which brought a white ſcurf all over him, drank the waters, and in a few weeks time, the ſpreading Scorbutick ferment being dinted, the blood purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſcales from the roots dryed and mortified, and pilled off, and he was cured.</p>
               <p>To which (as at the Heel of theſe Inſtances of cures of the Scurvy) we ſhall (by way of concluſion) only ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join ſomewhat in ſhort concerning Scorbutick <hi>Hemorrhoids:</hi> and that not only for the opening thoſe which are inward, ſwelled, and obſtructed, but alſo for binding, cloſing, and healing thoſe which are too open; in both cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the Scorbutick Acidum of the blood: In the one looſning the impacted, and cloſe rivetted Acidum, which binds and ſwells the veins: and in the other ſweetning or dinting the Acidum (which lacerated and wounded the veins) gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binding up and healing the Orifices
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33968:31"/>thereof for the future: of which in order as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>Scorbutick Hemorrhoids.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Two and thirtieth cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Ker</hi> of <hi>Eaton</hi> (in the year 1677) laboured under greivous pains of the inward Hemerrhoids, had a conſtant pain of thoſe parts, but eſpecially when nature was to diſcharge its burden by ſiege, which was very afflictive to him, cauſing him great grief for near a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a year; had advice of a Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, but found no benefit, till he came to the waters, which he drank regularly, for ten or twelve days: whereby the Scorbutick Acidum (which was let down into and had bound and ſwelled the Hermorrhoidal veſſels) was ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and dinted, as he returned home perfectly well, and continues ſo ever ſince.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman acquainted me that the waters open the <hi>Hemorrhoid</hi> veins, which doth him a great kindneſs in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his health: upon the account whereof he drinks them every year.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:33968:32"/>
               <head>Scorbutick Hermorrhoids.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Three and thirtieth cure.</head>
               <p>ANd that the waters are proper, not only for the opening the <hi>Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoids,</hi> where obſtructed, as aforeſaid: but alſo for the cloſing and healing them when too open, was obſervable from a Doctor of my acquaintance, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring with a more then ordinary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of <hi>Hemorrhoidal</hi> blood, and that for about ſeven years, was at firſt very ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous of drinking the waters, fearing leaſt they ſhould open the aforenamed veins too much. But being incouraged by the ſucceſs he ſaw others have, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, and to his great ſatisfaction and even admiration found great help thereby.</p>
               <p>That theſe waters purifie the blood and cure the Scurvy, even in ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have been tainted with it in a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, is evident from the large expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience had thereof by Dr. <hi>Wittie</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> late wars, when the Garriſon which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> kept by Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmly</hi> in the Caſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> after a few weeks ſiege, whether fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the air of the ſea, or a bad diet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> want of exerciſe, his men were moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33968:32"/>them fallen into the Scurvy, eſpecially the Country-Gentlemen who had fled in thither, who were miſerably troubled with it: as many of them as drank of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water, were perfectly and ſpeedily cured, which ſome of them uſed without any other means. And many inſtances (as Dr. <hi>Wittie</hi> ſaith) of perſons of quality might be brought in, who have been highly tainted with all the Symptoms that attend the Scurvy and <hi>Cachexy,</hi> and were upon the very brink of the Dropſie, having their legs ſwelled <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who have found perfect cures, on which account, they were conſtant frequenters of it. Only before we conclude this Claſſis of <hi>Scarbrough</hi>'s Maladies, it will not be amiſs to take notice, that as the Scruvy doth chiefly depend upon the depravation of the ferment of the Stomach, towards the rectification and reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of which, the waters notably contribute: ſo likewiſe the other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of depravations of the Stomach, whence dejections of appetite, and an ingendring of tough Phlegm, which in ſome perſons theſe waters carry off by vomit; of which I ſhall give this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing inſtance.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33968:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. Bilbrough</hi> Jun. of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> finds, that as often as his Stomach declines (as it yearly by times doth) when he drinks the waters, always the firſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it makes him vomit much tough Phlegm, then paſſeth downward the reſt by ſiedge, and in a few daies recruits his Stomach again very well.</p>
               <p>Where we might alſo ſhew theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are ſo proper to the Stomach, and to the reſtoring its ferment, as that they effectually aſſiſt in the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off ſuch depraved matter, as through exceſs by debauchery lies heavy and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the Stomack, and by a longer ſtay in the body, might become the Seminary of many diſeaſes, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Surfeits, Scurvyes, Dropſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by preventing ſuch fruits as are the natural product and off-ſpring of ſuch Seminaries: concerning which (if we might not thereby give incouragement towards the tranſgreſſing the bounds of Temperance and Moderation) we could give conſiderable inſtances, ſave that we Judge ſuch here not to be Exemplary, and therefore of deſign forbear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:33968:33"/>
               <head>Melancholy <hi>or the</hi> Hypochondriacal Flatus.</head>
               <p>THe next diſeaſe we intend in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to treat of, and to innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the cures thereof performed by the waters, is <hi>Melancholy</hi> called the <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Hypochondriacus,</hi> or <hi>Hypochondriacal Melancholy,</hi> and the Diſeaſes ſpringing from <hi>Melancholy;</hi> which Diſeaſe, we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is cauſed from the irregularities of the ferments of the Stomach and <hi>Spleen,</hi> whence ſome impurities (otherwiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable by the vigor and genuine tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the ferments) are heaped up in the blood, chiefly in reference to its elaboration into Animal Spirits, which being depraved in their <hi>Minera</hi> or Shop, are inſtead of being (if I may ſo ſay) tranſlucid congeneal Spirits (the genuine product of a right and natural <hi>geneſis</hi> thereof, and thence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the obſolving the functions of the body) ſoyled with a clodding va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, and darkned with a miſty and foggy ſteam, perverts the Phanſie, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times inverting the regular <hi>Idea</hi>'s there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:33968:34"/>
               <p>The degrees of which Diſeaſe are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, yea intended or remitted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as thoſe Spirits are (in their firſt hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or ſhapings) more or leſs ſoyled with thoſe noxious ſteams, and clouding va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors, which ſteams and fogs receive all their meaſures from the ferments of the <hi>Stomach</hi> and <hi>Spleen,</hi> as they are more or leſs vitiated, from the error of which ferment ariſeth <hi>Indigeſtion</hi> or <hi>Crudities,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> or rather <hi>Chaos</hi> of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid clouds or ſteams; and from it alſo is produced <hi>Wind</hi> or <hi>Flatus,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per fruit or effect of <hi>Indigeſtion.</hi> For wherever the generation of the Spirits are, the firſt ſprings thereof (whether <hi>Stomach, Spleen,</hi> or arterial veſſels) we ſuppoſe to be the chief <hi>Minera</hi> of this Diſeaſe, (whoſe deep rootedneſs and inward receſs is the main reaſon of the difficuly of its cure,) which accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the reluctancy of the ferments in the error of Digeſtion, bringeth on the incoarcible <hi>Flatus,</hi> whereby it diſplayes it ſelf into all thoſe various ſymptoms which attend this Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe Animal Spirits are the moſt ſublime and etherial parts of the body, and neareſt a-kin to the Soul; are the <hi>medium</hi> betwixt the Soul and Body,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33968:34"/>and as ſuch, are (we ſuppoſe) not only the vehicle but alſo the mirror of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul: and in as much as the Soul acts in the body <hi>juxta indolem organo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> according to the capacity, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, texture, temperature or craſis of its vehicle, which alſo has its ſprings from the alimentary and ſanguineous juyces elaborated by their peculiar fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: wherefore if the conſtitution of theſe Spirits from the vigour of the ferments (ſequeſtring all <hi>Heterogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi>) prove genuine, and thence the looking-glaſs of the Soul becomes pure and polite. In ſuch conſtitutions (I ſay) the ſoul, through the clarity of the Regimen of the Spirits, takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and ſolace in its vehicle, cauſing generous reflections, and ſhaping per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicatious <hi>Idea</hi>'s, helping (as we ſay in our <hi>Hydrol. Chym.</hi> 122.) accurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of phanſie, ſolidity of judgment and tenaciouſneſs of <hi>Memory.</hi> But if through the deficiency of the ferments, ariſe <hi>Indigeſtion</hi> and <hi>Crudities,</hi> thence the untamable <hi>Flatus</hi> or <hi>Wind,</hi> and from both dark ſteams, whence the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Spirits are mudded in their firſt ſprings, and their conſtitution or <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> ſoiled through foggy Scorbutick
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33968:35"/>miſts. then and there is laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this deeply rooted Malady; whereby the imaginative part is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (the fanſie by a Melancholy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por being clouded,) and thence as from its natural ſource, ariſeth from the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularities and diſturbed phanſies of <hi>Hypochondriacal Melancholy:</hi> For the Stomach, Spleen, arterial juyces, with the ferments thereof, as they are (by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) imployed in order to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of Animal Spirits, are <hi>Vulcan</hi>'s Shop, where materials lie for forging all <hi>Idea</hi>'s, and <hi>Minerva</hi>'s Nurſery, where are the ground-plots and ſeeds of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>Now if the depravation of the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in order to the hewing forth or generation of Animal Spirits, meet or interfeer with other manner of errors of the ferments as appertaining to the ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary juyces (as they are to circulate the various ſtades of the ſeveral digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in order to the nouriſhment of the body or ſupply of what daily tranſpires;) then, I ſay, is produced a complication of <hi>Melancholy</hi> with the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> yea the one graduates or heightens the other in their reſpective depravations, whence it is that <hi>Melancholy,</hi> and the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33968:35"/>go hand in hand. It rarely happens that <hi>Melancholy</hi> is brought to any conſiderable height, but is twiſted and complicated with the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the contrary not often holds good) from which complication is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally produced a <hi>leſa imaginatio,</hi> (the uſual product of that diſeaſe;) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſometimes the heightnings of the one, ſingly conſidered, effects it, and from this depravedneſs of the fancy, it is that the Patient is affected now in one part (ready to dye upon it,) and preſently in another remote part (and muſt die of that, and forthwith too) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So they coyn to themſelves hundreds of Miſeries, as to this or the other part, and as many deaths ere one of either ſort really ſiezeth upon them.</p>
               <p>We deſign not here (becauſe we ſtudy brevity) to ſhew how and after what manner the waters operate, and how other additional helps (by way of advice) contribute to the cure of this ſo deeply ſeated Diſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e: how it abſterſeth the firſt veſſels ſtrengthneth the ferment of the St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nach, procures an appetite, helps d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtion, promotes the clarity of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gimen of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33968:36"/>Spirits by carrying away the cauſe of impure and <hi>Scorbutick</hi> ſteams,) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the cauſe of Wind, (which two laſt are moſt-what the ſcene, where and whence moſt of the Tragical Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms of this Diſeaſe are acted:) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies the tone of the <hi>viſcera,</hi> rectifies their genuine ferments, ſweetens the blood, conduceth to the production of laudable nutritive juyces, (which, how far theſe may go towards the cure of moſt Diſeaſes, we refer to better judgments to determine;) and thence brings on a good habit of body, and health the ſequel of all. To inſiſt large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon which, is beſides our preſent purpoſe; we ſhall therefore (which we chiefly aim at) only confine our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe herein, to number a few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable inſtances of the efficacy of theſe waters in the cure thereof, which are as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:33968:36"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Woodyears</hi> Caſe, a Gentleman in <hi>York.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The firſt Cure.</head>
               <p>AT <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> 1667. began the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of <hi>Melancholy</hi> or <hi>Hypocond. Wind,</hi> (being the Paſſion of Sorrow for the loſs of his beloved Son,) which Diſeaſe gradually grew to that height, as in about eighteen Moneths time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt beginning thereof, it brought upon him a <hi>Virtigo</hi> or <hi>Megrim,</hi> ſo as he thought all went round. At <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> 72. he had two fits (one ſoon after the other) as he ſate in his chair, which for the time deprived him of all ſenſe; after which, he had (as accompanying Symptoms) pains all over him, with great oppreſſion of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; a general indiſpoſition, ſhortneſs of Breath, want of Appetite, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vomited what he took, had a great weakneſs and unſteddineſs, yet ſeeming great weight upon his head, ſo as he could not ſtoop, or ſcarce move it but gradually; had ſtrange fancies; the leaſt noiſe had ſo deep an
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33968:37"/>impreſſion upon him, as was enough almoſt (as he thought) to have ſtruck him dead. Three days after his two fits he was extremely ſick with a faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirits as if to death, which ſo much weaked him as he was not able to walk over his Chamber without lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for four Moneths: during which time he had many of thoſe ſudden Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leptick fits, conſtantly at change and full of the Moon, and fainted all over his Spirits for ſome hours together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in an Agony with weeping, which fainting fits would hold for nine hours at a time, with great ſtruglings as if convulſed; upon all which, the <hi>pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata animi</hi> had originally the greateſt influence.</p>
               <p>He had the advice of two eminent Phyſicians, who ran through ſeveral cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Phyſick with him, giving him Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, Purges, ordering him blooding by the Hemorrhoids, Steel Preparations, &amp;c. Who, when none of theſe would do, they adviſed him to go for <hi>Scarbrough-Spaw,</hi> whither in <hi>July,</hi> 1673. he went, and drank the waters according to advice three weeks: For the firſt ten dayes whereof he was very weak, had a fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs upon his Spirits, found no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33968:37"/>or benefit thereby: at length Dr. <hi>Wittie</hi> (then attending the waters) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him to ride abroad upon the Hills. As he was riding, a ſudden griping took him round his body for half an hour, and then an extreme purging came on him that he had four Stools in an hour, with extremity of gripings before each Stool. This purging began at two in the afternoon, but the gripings began to abate before morning, inſomuch that it became rather a pleaſure to have Stools than otherwiſe, ſo continued all next day and night after (without drinking the waters) in which time he grew ſo ſteddy, compos'd and ſtrong in his head as he could ſtep out of his bed to the ſtool without any help, although he continued purging 4 times every hour. The ſecond morning early the Doctor adviſed him to put on his cloaths (ſince he was ſo ſtrong) and walk to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> where (he according to advice) drank only two pints of water, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in going he had four ſtools, yet after drinking the waters he had only one or two there, but none in return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and (what was remarkable) in going to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> he walked faſter than the Doctor, to the admiration of all that were by.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:33968:38"/>
               <p>After the aforeſaid purgings, he drank the waters for eleven mornings, which then wrought ſo moderately as it had a moſt conſiderable and wonderful effect upon him, his ſymptoms all abated and gradually went off, got a good Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and digeſtion, the <hi>flatus</hi> (with its cauſes) was ſuppreſſed, which before ſat upon the skirts of the Spirits, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane of the Brain and Stomach, whence his <hi>Vertigo</hi> went away, the load or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſs upon his head was taken off, it became ſteddy, his faintneſs and ſickneſs ceaſed, the ſoyling ſteams or vapors which perverted and darkned the <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of the Spirits (whence with other concurring cauſes happened the <hi>leſa imaginatio</hi>) were diſcuſſed, prevented, and in fine, he thereby became lively, brisk, and chearful beyond expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even to the Admiration of all thoſe (whether in City or Country) who knew him in his former long lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring weakneſs. — He has ever ſince made his Annual viſits to theſe waters at their ſeaſon, and has to (his great ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction) injoyed his health without the leaſt Relapſe or Symptom of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer dreadful Malady.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:33968:38"/>
               <p>The Symptoms of whoſe Diſeaſe were ſignal Teſtimonies that the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were perverted, the nutritive and Sanguineous juyces were become depraved and Spurious, an incoarcible <hi>flatus</hi> was powerful, and that the ſteams and vitiated juyces had darkned and clouded the <hi>Regimen</hi> of the Animal Spirits, whence the <hi>leſa maginatio,</hi> and that the <hi>flatus</hi> by occult paſſages and rubs of the veſſels bore ſtrongly upon the <hi>meninges</hi> or tender film of the brain, whence came the ſeeming weight and yet unſteddineſs of his head, as alſo bore forcibly upon the original of the Nerves in the brain, whence his Virti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginous and Epiliptick fits, and ſmiting or ſuffocating the Spirits in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ducts, as alſo being much penned up (excepting as aforeſaid) in the Stomach, ſtrengthneth the <hi>Tunicles</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, bearing upon the breathing-holes of the vital ferment (the parent of Digeſtion) tranſmitted from the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries into the Stomach, ſuſpended its function, whence ſickneſſes and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; And how the waters orderly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken according to advice, anſwered all theſe indications, or as many of them as was needful, we (for brevity-ſake) wave farther to inlarge.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:33968:39"/>
               <p>From the aforeſaid remarkable cauſe and cure, we might take an occaſion to raiſe a diſcourſe how the paſſions of the mind became the efficients and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of many Symptoms and Diſeaſes, eſpecially ſuch as attend Hypocondraiſm in Men and hyſterical fits in Women; how they influence the ferments, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, chyliferous and ſanguineous juyces, tone of the <hi>viſcera,</hi> organs of the Spirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> perverting the firſt, diſturbing and ſuſpending the ſecond, alienating or vitiating the third, alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fourth, inverting the order of the fifth, and all in order to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of ſeveral Diſeaſes, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly emerging therefrom, but that I muſt re-mind my ſelf of my deſigned brevity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The ſecond cure.</head>
               <p>THe Right Honorable the Lord <hi>Roos</hi> had been much troubled with Hypochondriack wind, which ſtole away both his appetite and digeſtion, and cauſed an eminent decay of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and ſtrength, and ſo filled his head with fumes, that he was often taken with dizzineſs and Melancholy fancies,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33968:39"/>after long methods of Phyſick preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by ſeveral learned Phyſicians (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in though he ever found much good, yet his Diſtemper was frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning:) his Lord-ſhip came to theſe waters, wherein he found ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit in all the reſpects aforeſaid, that he now injoyes a conſtant ſtate of health, this (when firſt writ) being the third year wherein his Lord-ſhip viſits <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> being then become much more lively and fleſhy than formerly, and found good encouragement to continue his Annual viſits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Third Cure.</head>
               <p>MRS. <hi>Robinſon</hi> of <hi>Buckton</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt fifty and ſixty years of age) laboured under a grievous and inveterate <hi>Head-ach</hi> on one ſide, which was very violent, proceeding from the <hi>Flatus Hypochondraicus,</hi> having fixed it ſelf chiefly upon that part, and was alſo highly Scorbutick, having the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> in a great meaſure: The pain of her head was ſo ſtrong as put her upon the trial of many Phyſitians, and had the beſt of their advice, but moſt-what in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33968:40"/>vain: at length drank theſe waters, and in fourteen dayes time ſhe found her pain abate and gradually go off, and within a moneth ſhe was perfectly well both as to her head-ach, (which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would not bend to ordinary means) and alſo was cured of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning in very good health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fourth Cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Thomas Birbeck</hi> of <hi>Sheffeild</hi> in <hi>York ſhire,</hi> was ſo afflicted with that <hi>Flatus Hypocond.</hi> as it affected his head very much with a dizzineſs or vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiginous motion that he ſcarce durſt preach in the Pulpit: was in a languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition in this diſeaſe, being full of fears and fancies, applied himſelf to the waters, and the firſt year found ſo much good thereby as incouraged him to come the next year after, and then he was cured, and for many years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a healthful and chearful man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33968:40"/>
               <head>The Fifth Cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>G. Smith</hi> of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed</hi> practitioner in Phyſick, fell into an extream heat and ſharpneſs of Urine, with a continual dyſury, after which did immediately ſucceed moſt grievous ſymptoms of Hypochondriach Melancholy, <hi>viz.</hi> Dizzineſs in his head, Dimneſs of ſight, Difficulty of breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Oppreſſion at Stomach, and Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of meat, being voided raw, which himſelf, with others ſufficiently learned, did in vain labour to remove, ſo as he was forced to keep his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber almoſt ſix moneths together, even deſpairing of a recovery; he came to theſe waters and drank three weeks, and returned home in good health and chearfulneſs of Spirit; for two years after he came again, and reſolved, while God ſpared life to continue his Annual viſits, notwithſtanding the diſtance, being above an hundred and twenty miles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:33968:41"/>
               <head>The Sixth Cure.</head>
               <p>MRS. <hi>Elizabeth Scremerſton</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham</hi> was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for a long time with the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, which had changed her complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and made her exceeding ſwarthy, with three weeks drinking ſhe found a perfect recovery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Seventh Cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Robert Lever</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Bolam</hi> in <hi>Northumberland</hi> was exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled with Hipocondriach Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly for the ſpace of eight years, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with frequent extention and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion of the Nerves, which when the fit was gone off left him ſo feeble that he was not able to walk till he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſome reſt, he was often dizzy in his his head, which ſo clouded his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that he became uncapable ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for a quarter of a year together of diſcharging the duties of his Office. He was ſeveral times at the other <hi>Spaw</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:33968:41"/>in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> where though he found ſome benefit, yet the ſymptoms return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In 1663. he came to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> and drank a whole week, yet without any benefit till the Phyſician then at the waters, <hi>viz.</hi> Doctor <hi>Wittie</hi> was called to ſee the fit, wherein he ſeemed to be almoſt diſtracted, who judged it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to preſcribe ſome other helps pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the caſe for two or three dayes, and furniſhed him with ſome Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficks to be uſed with the waters, and ſet him on again, adviſing him to drink ten dayes more; after three dayes he found eminent degrees of recovery, all the ſymptoms abating, and went from the waters very healthful and chearful, who (praiſed be Almighty God) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Eighth Cure</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>M. Darrel</hi> of <hi>Porſtow</hi> in <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln</hi>-Shire is by times much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the <hi>Hypocond. Flatus,</hi> finds much benefit by drinking theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wherefore he frequents them eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year, ſometimes he is for rear ſix
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33968:42"/>moneths exceſſive Melancholy, cares for no company, but loves retirement: And by an orderly taking of theſe waters finds preſent relief, when no other Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine he has taken at home has ſucceeded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Ninth Cure.</head>
               <p>MRS. <hi>Elizabeth Newcome</hi> of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> was eight or nine years together ſo afflicted with this Malady, joyned with extreme oppreſſion of the ſtomach and back, with flitting heats, as if ſhe had been in a violent Feaver, perpetual coſtiveneſs and diz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zineſs of the head before the violence of the hot fit, ſhe found a ſharp ſtinging in the wriſt of her right arm as if a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knife was thruſt into it, and when the fit was upon her, ſhe would fall into excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great frights from any the leaſt noiſe, as the crowing of a Cock or the barking of a Dog, and when it was gone off ſhe would be as ſore as if ſhe were beaten: It had reſiſted all medicines, till coming to theſe waters, ſhe found good ſucceſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:33968:42"/>
               <head>The Tenth Cure.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Scotch</hi> Gentlewoman, being in years, was much afflicted with Hypochondraiſm and the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a great diſorder at her Stomach, drank the waters in great exceſs, was brought low and very weak, but after a while ſhe recruited to her former ſtrength, and the bad ſymptoms went off.</p>
               <p>Here I could reckon upon ſeveral perſons more who have by the order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe of theſe wates found much bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in this very Malady. But at preſent let thoſe in <hi>tranſitu</hi> ſerve.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> Stone.</head>
            <p>THe next Diſeaſe in order we here propoſe to treat on, as curable by the waters, is that formidable, afflicting and excruciating malady the <hi>Stone,</hi> where we do not mean to aſcribe that efficacy to theſe mineral waters as to melt or diſſolve any large confirmed ſtone of what ſize ſoever, fixed in the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33968:43"/>Kidneys or Bladder; For that we whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny, and judge ſuch perſons who labour under the anxiety of ſuch large Stones as cannot without danger be brought away by the common paſſages of the ureters, neck of the Bladder, &amp;c. not capable I ſay of receiving much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit hereby. But are rather to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the skill and cure of the <hi>Lithotomiſt,</hi> to <hi>Mars</hi> rather than <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> to the ſharpneſs of the knife than to the accurateneſs of the waters.</p>
            <p>But that theſe waters have a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able efficacy upon ſuch as labour under gravel, ſmaller ſtones, (ſuch as are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable) and in taking away, or alleviating their grievous ſymptoms, the uſual at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants and products thereof, amongſt which, that of <hi>Strangury</hi> is to be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as a frequent ſymptom and almoſt neceſſary product of the Stone, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, that ſometimes may proceed from other cauſes:) what remarkable efficacy (I ſay) theſe waters orderly taken, have upon ſuch, let the few fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing inſtances ſpeak, which in the main may be ſufficient to blazon its ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to the world in this very particular Malady, that ſo none through prejudice
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33968:43"/>or ignorance may deny themſelves that benefit which God in nature holds forth to them in this Mineral Spring.</p>
            <p>As to the cauſes of petrefaction whether in the <hi>Macro</hi> or <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> but particularly that of the <hi>Lithiaſis, viz.</hi> the cauſes of ingendring the Stone in the Reins or Bladder of humane bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, we inſiſt largely and <hi>de induſtria</hi> in our <hi>Lithologia Phyſica.</hi> (not yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant) And as for the ſymptoms, they are ſo well known by every one who is afflicted with this Diſeaſe as we need not by numbring them tell what they are, wherefore we ſhall immediately deſcend to the intended particulars as followeth.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Firſt Caſe.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>John Beaumont</hi> of <hi>Franck-foſs</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> his wife had been for very many years ſubject to a grievous fit of the Stone, for which ſhe had taken much advice, though with little ſucceſs, ſhe went afterwards to <hi>Knarsbrough</hi> and drank thoſe waters, but found no benefit: then her husband brought her to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> which water brought
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33968:44"/>away the matter of the Stone in Gravel and Sand to a great proportion even in one weeks time, and for five years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (being then ſo long to the firſt writing hereof) ſhe had no neceſſity of returning to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> being free of all ſymptoms.—To which I may add what I lately by letter received from a Relation of the aforeſaid Gentle-womans, and (my worthy friend) that ſhe received ſo much benefit by theſe waters, and for this fourteen years hath been ſo well that ſhe never needed to make a ſecond viſit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Second Caſe.</head>
               <p>AN old man of eighty ſix years of age, has frequented the <hi>Span</hi> for twelve or thirteen years, finding much good thereby every year for the Stone, had extreme and moſt violent pains and grievous torments, even ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make him cry forth aloud, ſo as he might be heard at a great diſtance, yea his torment in thoſe parts were ſo ſtrong that (to uſe his own words) he would have forgiven any one who would have knocked him on the head, he drank plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33968:44"/>of the waters, ſometimes fifteen pints in a morning, found great relief thereby: the benefit he reaps incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth him to come every year, and was here this very laſt year 78, from whoſe own mouth I had the aforeſaid Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Third Caſe.</head>
               <p>THE old Lady <hi>Rhodes</hi> of <hi>Balbrough,</hi> was grievouſly afflicted with the ſymptoms of the <hi>Stone;</hi> who found great help and relief by the drinking theſe waters; yea, and by what I could learn was cured thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fourth Caſe.</head>
               <p>SR. <hi>J. H.</hi> of <hi>York</hi> (now a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Parliament) drank the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for ſeveral years, finding thereby he voided much gravel, and was more chearful afterwards: Then for five years by times was frequently afflicted with the ſymptoms of the <hi>Stone,</hi> having
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33968:45"/>difficulty of Urine (or <hi>dyſuria</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ming away drop by drop with pain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Stone came away, but ſtill eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year Gravel came away, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> more at eaſe.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1677. he went and drank the waters, before which for Moneth or more, had a great <hi>dyſuria</hi> or difficulty of urine, making none b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with great pain: The firſt day he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worſe, the ſecond day alſo worſer, yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the third day was worſe and worſe the waters mean-while paſſing, but not well. And upon the night after the third day, a ſtone, to the bigneſs of a Date-ſtone came away, which was a ſolid confirmed ſtone; then all the bad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Symptoms ceaſed, and he had perfect eaſe.</p>
               <p>The next year after (which was the laſt year) he came to the waters, and upon the third-day morning (after the firſt drinking) voided another leſs ſtone about the bigneſs of a vetch, which was angular, but not of ſo firm a texture by much as the former, which he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, and ſince which has had paſſage of his water very well, having not the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33968:45"/>leaſt of thoſe troubleſome ſymptoms which uſually attend the Stone, he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that upon every years drinking the waters, his Stomach was much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited and digeſtion bettered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fifth Caſe.</head>
               <p>A Lady of <hi>Scotland,</hi> no leſs virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Morals than noble in birth, had two violent fits of the Stone in her own Country, with extream ſharp pain even to ſwoonings, ſo as they almoſt deſpaired of her life, after the ſevere Paroxiſme was over, ſhe came, by her Phy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſicians advice to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> drank the waters regularly, whereby in a few dayes ſhe voided a ſtone, which her Ladyſhip ſhewed me, it was angular, yet came away with little pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Sixth Caſe.</head>
               <p>A Merchant of <hi>York</hi> (Mr. <hi>A. T.</hi>) laboured of a fit of the Stone, after ſome other Medicaments I adviſed him, he drank the waters, whereby he paſſed away a little ſtone, and ſo the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33968:46"/>Symptoms ceaſed and he was at eaſe For which very purpoſe he drank <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> waters moſt-what every year, and the with good ſucceſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Seventh Caſe</head>
               <head type="sub">Which is Mr. <hi>G. Waugh</hi> of <hi>New Caſtle's</hi> Caſe, ſent by way of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Dr. <hi>Wittie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SR. I judge my ſelf obliged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> give my teſtimony of the <hi>Spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and its good effects in my Caſe, and firſt I bleſs God that he has afforde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me ſo great help by it, and alſo I let you know that it proved effectual almoſt beyond my firſt belief of the waters even to my admiration. In the year 69. at my firſt viſiting of the Well the water did not only bring away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> confirmed Stone as large as any Date ſtone, with its bed in which it lay but as I found did alſo ſoften and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve what was more in my body, ſo that at one urine (as I remember) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> voided above a dozen ſtones, moſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them as large as a white Peaſe, which did lye in the baſon as ſtones, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33968:46"/>draining the water off, and thinking to take them up, they would not bear their own weight, but betwixt my fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers became ſand, and theſe I voided the very day I left the <hi>Spaw.</hi> At my return in 1670. I had not drank eight pints of the water the firſt morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a large quantity of the tartarous tough matter that breeds the Stone came away, which I know was cauſed by the vertue of the water.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I am your, &amp;c.</hi> George Waugh.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Eighth Caſe.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Emmerſon</hi> of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> having violent pain from the Stone, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was exceedingly enfeebled, drank the waters (in the year 1677.) pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty plentifully, and at one time (as he obſerved) about a ſpoonful and a half of gravel paſſed from him; drank the waters alſo the laſt year with great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, had a pain in his back from the ſtone or gravel in the Kidneys before
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33968:47"/>he drank them, but upon drinking, it went away, and he was as well as ever he was (according to his own words) in his life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Ninth Caſe.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Chriſtopher Keld</hi> of <hi>Newby</hi> near <hi>Scarbrough</hi> had been many years ſubject to violent fits of the <hi>Stone,</hi> and falling into one of his uſual fits, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to mind, that he had heard this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter commended in the caſe; ſo as he ſent immediately for ſome bottles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and drank betwixt two or three quarts, which within leſs than half an hour, cauſed him to void ſeveral ſtones, beſides much gravel, which gave him perfect eaſe, ſo as for ſeven years after he had not another fit. But then it ſeizing on him again, he applied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the ſame remedy, with like ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Tenth Caſe.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Stow</hi> of <hi>Newton</hi> upon <hi>Trent</hi> in <hi>Nottingham</hi>-ſhire, his Son being cut for the Stone, in order to the heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33968:47"/>of the wound in the neck of the bladder, firſt drank <hi>Knarsbrough-Spaw</hi>-waters, but afterwards hearing of the ſame of <hi>Scarbrough</hi>-waters did about eight or nine years (before the firſt writing hereof) make a journey thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by which they found ſo much and more real benefit in that diſeaſe of the of the Stone than they had before, that they never after returned to <hi>Knarsbrough</hi> but have been conſtant drinkers of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi>-waters, either going thither, or elſe ſending for the waters to <hi>Newton,</hi> though it be near thirty miles further diſtant than the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Eleventh Caſe.</head>
               <p>THe Apothecary of <hi>Scarbrough</hi>'s Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has found much good by the waters for the Stone, who has ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times voided a ſpoonful of red ſand or gravel, and has drank them theſe many years.</p>
               <p>To all which we might add the Caſe of a Merchant in <hi>London,</hi> of Mr. <hi>W. Kitching</hi> who keeps the chief Inne at <hi>Grimsby</hi> in <hi>Lincoln</hi>-ſhire by the Sea ſide) of Mr. <hi>Skehough</hi> a School-maſter
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33968:48"/>in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. who all received ſo much good hereby for the Stone, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them for ſome years to frequent the waters.</p>
               <p>That theſe waters ſometimes diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and brings on a fit of the Stone to ſome perſons, who poſſibly never had one before, (I think) an evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the excellency of it vertue: For many are inclinable to the Stone, and perhaps as yet know not, but might (if the taking theſe waters did not prevent) go on towards the Fabrick of ſome large cofirmed ſtone, which then by its bulk might be incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any cure ſave that of the knife. But theſe waters by their powerful effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, ſuſpends further growth to the Stone, diſlodgeth thoſe already bred, and either ſplits them into leſſer ſtone or moulders them into gravel, and ſo paſſes them off in a ſtream or flood of urine (which otherwiſe might if le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alone grow two big for the paſſages) or if they be no bigger, than may glide through the veſſels and orifices, to carn them away in their intire form, and hence I ſay it is that ſometimes a ſharp fit (upon the drinking thereof) hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, which to judge otherwiſe doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33968:48"/>were to do manifeſt injuſtice to them, becauſe hereby <hi>Knarsbrough-Spaw</hi> might as equally be impeached, as <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> in that ſome have upon drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe waters been ſeiſed with a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fit of the Stone; For inſtance, the Earl of <hi>Twadal</hi> about four year ago (as his Lordſhip acquainted me) even while he was drinking the waters of <hi>Knarbrough,</hi> was ſeized with a violent fit of the Stone. And Mr. <hi>Juſtice</hi> an Attorney, being in health, out of compliaſance drank five glaſſes of the Sulphur water of <hi>Knarsbrough</hi> laſt <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> which, not paſſing, gave him a Surfeit, ſo as he afterwards vomited and purged all that he took, thence fell into a great languor of Spirits, and thence into violent convulſive fits, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered his life. Muſt therefore the former, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſweet Spaw-waters be accuſed of a petrifying property, or muſt thence of neceſſity the other, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Sulphur</hi>-water be accounted dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to drink on? which conſequences, how adapted to our preſent purpoſe, we leave to the judicious reader to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
               <p>Theſe waters are alſo peculiar againſt the heat, inflamation and ulcer of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33968:49"/>
                  <hi>reins,</hi> correcting the heat and ſharpneſs of urine, expelling the mucous matter which ſometimes obſtructs the paſſages of the urine, which often times cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſame ſymptoms, and is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to be the Stone in the bladder; when yet there is none there, waſhing through and cleanſing all the urinous paſſages</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The Reliques of a <hi>Clap.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe waters are likewiſe excellent good againſt the reliques of a Clap, and cleanſes away the dregs of a bad Mercurial method, helps the piſſing of blood, and ſtrengthneth the ſeminal veſſels, the malignity of the Diſeaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt removed by due Medicines.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Gonorrhea.</head>
               <p>THe waters regularly drank ſafely ſtayes the <hi>Gonorrhea.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="instance">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:33968:49"/>
                  <head>The firſt Inſtance.</head>
                  <p>A Gentleman that had got a Clap, having had the uſual ſymptoms upon him many Moneths, which had exceedingly impaired his ſtrength: who committing himſelf for cure unto two able Phyſitians, who in a few weeks took off all the pains, and other ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, only a fluid <hi>Gonorrhea</hi> remained which reſiſted Medicines, even the moſt proper they could preſcribe, and that for ſeveral weeks after the virulency of the Diſeaſe was gone, was adviſed to drink of theſe waters, where within ten days he was perfectly cured, and ſince has begotten Children.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="instance">
                  <head>The ſecond Inſtance.</head>
                  <p>ANother had got a grievous <hi>Gonorrhea</hi> which through the ſharpneſs of the humor, made ſuch a corroſion upon the neck of the Bladder, that he piſſed blood with exceeding great pain, to the great abatement of his natural ſtrength. It had reſiſted what advice he had met with in the Country, till coming to theſe waters, he was perfectly cured in a very few dayes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33968:50"/>
            <head>Agues.</head>
            <p>THe next diſeaſe, according to our propoſed method, we are to treat of, as curable by the waters, are <hi>Agues,</hi> which are nothing elſe but broken or interrupted <hi>Feavers,</hi> whoſe different ſpaces of intervals and acceſſes made from the more or leſs frequent imbibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the offending <hi>febril Acidum</hi> doth moſtwhat, if not ſolely, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them into <hi>Quotidian, Tertian,</hi> double <hi>Tertian</hi> and <hi>Quartane,</hi> which (I ſay) in their root are Feavers, being the ſame with them in their eſſential cauſes, only (as I ſaid) bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and thence have the interchanges of cold and heat, and admit of frequent periods: And that what a Feaver (ſtrictly ſo called) ſprings out with a long, and moſtwhat unbroken thread, theſe ſnap the thread, and begin and weave again, and that ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or later, as the offending <hi>febrile A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidum,</hi> (whether imbred, or <hi>ab extra,</hi> communicated from the air,) is partly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33968:50"/>tranſpired or precipitated, or in ſome adjacent veſſels depoſited, or by any of them for a time ſubjugated.</p>
            <p>What one has to ſay concerning Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, whether continued or broken, from a ſomewhat novel <hi>hypotheſis,</hi> we refer in the main to our <hi>Pyretologia,</hi> therefore ſhall at preſent apply our ſelves to the incumbent task, which is, Firſt, to ſhew that all broken Feavers, <hi>viz. Agues,</hi> are curable: Next, that they admit of various, and yet certain me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of cure: And laſtly, more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the purpoſe, are particularly (with ſome additionals) curable by theſe waters.</p>
            <p>Only here on the by, we would crave leave to ſay, that among the great improvements now on the wheel, in order to the better and more certain cure of Diſeaſes, it would doutleſs be none of the leaſt for Phyſicians to buſie themſelves in their Studies, and Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, how to promote this moſt laudable and uſeful eſſay, <hi>(viz.)</hi> how to break a Feaver, which I look upon as one of the Maſter-pieces of a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, (how unhappily it has been ſlipt hitherto I know not) to make a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſplit into <hi>Proxiſms,</hi> and then to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33968:51"/>cure them, which latter is moſt eaſily done; The former of which, how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently nature (put occaſionally upon ſome exigency or other) doth, with, or without the help of a Phyſitian, for the good of the Patient, many Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians in their obſervations can tell, which if they had but narrowly watched, and traced her in thoſe obſcure paths, might by ſearching have found out the knack, and ſo have helped her with ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther job in her pinch.</p>
            <p>If the former (I ſay) by the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Phyſitians, were but more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently proſecuted, and ſome progreſs made threin, towards the rendring it practical.</p>
            <p>It would then certainly be one of the eaſieſt things in the world, for Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians to cure the generality of Feavers, which otherwiſe cut off many hundreds (not to ſay more) of Patients.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> that all <hi>Agues</hi> are curable, the truth of which we are ready by matter of fact to make evident, where we doubt not but by infallible demonſtration to prove the cure of all manner of Agues, and that both certainly and ſafely, ſuppoſing mean-while there be ſtrength of nature enough to admit of</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33968:51"/>
            <p>As to the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Agues</hi> admit of various and yet certain me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of cure, is evident from the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practice of Phyſicians, ſome of whom cure <hi>Agues</hi> by one method, others by another.</p>
            <p>And as to the laſt <hi>(viz.)</hi> that <hi>Agues</hi> (which is more directly to the purpoſe) are particularly curable by <hi>Scarbrough</hi>-waters, leads me in to give an account of ſome few inſtances of cures perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thereby, which are as followeth.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The firſt.</head>
               <p>J. B. <hi>Jun.</hi> of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> had a <hi>Terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Ague</hi> ſeventeen weeks, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted him very much, drank the waters by advice, which in three dayes time brought him very low, yet continuing on drinking, he began to find his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach to recruit, got a good appetite, and good digeſtion of what he took, ſo his <hi>Ague</hi> went ſenſibly off, yea, in not many dayes it was quite gone, and he perfectly well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:33968:52"/>
               <head>The ſecond.</head>
               <p>MRS. <hi>G. C.</hi> A Merchants daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hull,</hi> laboured under<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tertian Ague,</hi> for about fifteen or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> teen weeks, which had vitiated the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her Stomach, debilitated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> appetite, and ſo weakned her as ſhe could walk but little, being much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with faintneſs and a general indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and laſſitude upon her, loſt her colour; came to the waters laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, took my advice, had only one eaſie fit, and no more all the time ſhe ſtaid, which was about fourteen dayes, recovered the ferment of her ſtomach, got a good appetite, and what ſhe took digeſted well, gathered ſtrength, ſo as ſhe could walk well, her fainting was gone, ſhe was chearful, got a good co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and returned home in very good health, and continued ſo, for I ſaw her Father about ſix weeks after, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted me his daughter continued ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:33968:52"/>
               <head>The third.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>G. Blackaller</hi> Rector of <hi>Etton</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> had been troubled with a double <hi>Quartan</hi> for the ſpace of nine moneths together with ſome ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> which appeared in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed ſpots in all the muſculous parts of the body. He went to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and at the very beginning his fits leſſened, and ſtaying three weeks he found a perfect cure, and had not the leaſt ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomps of either for five years after.</p>
               <p>I have often known (ſaith Doctor <hi>Wittie</hi>) inveterate <hi>Quartans</hi> cured by it, and other ſorts of <hi>Agues</hi> alſo, which have long reſiſted Medicines, have been conquered by the uſe hereof in a ſhort time.</p>
               <p>And for taking away the reliques of all inveterate <hi>Agues</hi> (thoſe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times tedious chronical diſeaſes) and of the ſmall-Pox and other diſeaſes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting relapſes, theſe waters are of admirable efficacy.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:33968:53"/>
            <head>The Jaundies.</head>
            <p>THis diſeaſe, as to its cauſes, chiefly depends upon obſtructions of the <hi>bilious</hi> veſſels leading into the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines, whereby that noble juyce (as an auxiliary ferment) aſſiſts in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of the offices in the ſecond Digeſtion, by agitating, fermenting, and further preparing the <hi>chiliferous</hi> juyce (tranſmitted from the ſtomach) helping the due ſeparation, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colation of the milky juyce into the lacteals diſſeminated along the Inteſtines in order to a future Sanguification, gives colour to the recrements, irritating the Periſtaltick motion of the ſpiral guts, in order to cleanſing work, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſeclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of excrements. This I ſay being obſtructed in its paſſage, flows by other veſſels into the maſs of blood, whoſe craſis it vitiates by giving it a high <hi>Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron</hi> Tincture, which nature partly in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilary veins throws into the habit of the body, witneſs the <hi>Saffron</hi> dye of all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal parts, and partly diſchargeth it,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33968:53"/>(as diſſolved in the <hi>ſerum</hi> or <hi>latex</hi> of the blood) by the <hi>emulgents</hi> into the urinary veſſels, whence the height of its <hi>Saffron</hi> tincture, both which (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) with the unſeparable ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of an univerſal laſſitude, indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhortneſs of breath and faintneſs) are the general, as well as certain index<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the <hi>Jaundies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore it is found by obſervation (the nurſery of knowledge) that thoſe Medicines which do open obſtructions are moſt prevalent in the cure hereof, amongſt which, thoſe who abound moſt with a fixed or volatile <hi>alcalie,</hi> or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of apperial Mineral Salts, are moſt effectual, eſpecially if a good round-working-purge precede, or that they be taken along with ſome proper purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. Now that theſe waters, as fraught Mineral apperient Salts, are (with ſome additional helps) adequate reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for this and other Diſeaſes ariſing from obſtructions, yea, even ſometimes the waters alone orderly taken) let their efficacy in theſe few following in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances declare to the world.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33968:54"/>
               <head>The Firſt Cure.</head>
               <p>SR <hi>John Legards</hi> Lady of <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> within a few miles of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> had a <hi>Jaundice</hi> that long reſiſted remedies in a rational method, and was perfectly cured by the <hi>Spaw</hi> in a few dayes, being thereto recommended by another Lady, who had experienced a cure in the ſame Diſeaſe. This was conſented to by her Phyſician Doctor <hi>Arnold.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Second Cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>W. Hodgſon</hi> Mimiſter of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> was for the ſpace of ſix years ever and anon falling into the <hi>Jaundies,</hi> eſpecially Spring and Fall: Nay, one time it continued upon him almoſt all the year, notwithſtanding his endeavours after a cure, after he was ſetled at <hi>Scarbrough</hi> he found a perfect cure by the <hi>Spaw.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33968:54"/>
               <head>The Third Cure.</head>
               <p>MAdam <hi>Elizabeth Strickland</hi> of <hi>Boynton</hi> in <hi>York-Shire,</hi> after the ſmall-Pox, fell into a <hi>Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> after that relapſed into a <hi>Tertian Ague,</hi> which terminated in the <hi>Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> after which (probably as an inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate ſymptom) followed a moſt grievous griping pain at the Stomach and Back, which ſeized on her by fits, ſometimes a month or two betwixt one another, accompanied with a vomiting up of whatſoever ſhe took, and after every fit her whole body would be as yellow as Gold. She had alſo a fulneſs and tenſion at Stomach and upon the region of the Liver, that ſhe could not indure it to be touched, nor could lie upon the right ſide. It had reſiſted all rational means that could be uſed, till the ſeaſon of the year coming on, Dr. <hi>Wittie</hi> (whoſe account this is) adviſed her Lady-ſhip to drink the waters, and fitted her with Medicines both prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative and concomitant, which ſhe did for fourteen dayes with very much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33968:55"/>being then almoſt half gone with Child, notwithſtanding after ſome months the fits returned as before, ſo as the next Summer ſhe drank the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters again (though at <hi>Boynton</hi> twelve miles from <hi>Scarbrough</hi>) ſhe was again ſomewhat better. But the Winter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing had moſt violent returns of her fits. The next year the Doctor advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to drink them at the Fountain, and to ſtay longer, which ſhe did for three weeks, and then after a months intermiſſion to ſend for freſh water eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, and drink ten dayes at home, her Ladiſhip being then young with Child, yet without any harm upon that account, ſince which ſhe had (God be thanked) no more fits, (it being when this was writ almoſt two years after) but was as healthful as in all her life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fourth Cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Palar</hi> of <hi>Nun-Nountain</hi> in <hi>York-Shire,</hi> was during his abode in the <hi>Southern</hi> parts much afflicted with the <hi>Jaundies,</hi> having the ſymptoms
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33968:55"/>which uſually attend that Diſeaſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted Doctor <hi>Dickenſon</hi> (who then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Oxford</hi> but is now an eminent Phyſician in <hi>London</hi>) whoſe advice was to get him down into his own country and to drink the waters of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> which he judged the beſt and moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain cure for him; whither accordingly he applied himſelf, and in not many dayes was perfectly cured.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only add ſomewhat remarkable concerning a Country man who had the <hi>Jaundies</hi> highly complicated with the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> with a great ſtiffneſs in his joynts, ſo as he could not ſtoop but with great pain and trouble; one day I ordered him a few doſes of volatile Spirits to be taken in his waters, upon which he found ſo great an alteration as that he could that very day (to the admiration of thoſe who were by) ſtoop to the ground with much eaſe, and (if I miſtake not) played at penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone upon the Sands.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:33968:56"/>
            <head>The Dropſie.</head>
            <p>THe next Diſeaſe in order is the <hi>Dropſie,</hi> which although at the firſt proſpect it may ſeem contradictory to reaſon, that the drinking of waters ſhould be effectual for the curing that Diſeaſe which chiefly conſiſts in a flood of watery latex, already heaped up in the maſs of blood, which is aforehand diluted with a wateriſhneſs; that which ſhould be carried off moſt-what byurine, being by obſtructions made to flow back upon the blood and thence makes it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſlow in its circulation, and brings it very nigh the analogy of a ſtanding Pool, ſhould by the adding more water be cured, is I ſay no leſs than a ſeeming <hi>Paradox,</hi> yet if we conſider the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary and Efficient cauſes thereof, and the manner of the waters working will eaſily remove that Jealouſie and confirm us in the belief of the contrary. And <hi>Firſt,</hi> if we conſider the immediate and efficient cauſes, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, the vitiated ferment of the Stomach (that primary
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33968:56"/>wheel of all Chronical maladies) the patron of the <hi>febricula</hi> and thirſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying <hi>Dropſical</hi> perſons, and next the tranſmitted <hi>Acidum</hi> impreſſed upon the reins, from whence ſometimes alone, and other while with ſome additional <hi>mucous</hi> matter, happen obſtructions of thoſe parts, which are the principal <hi>Emunctories</hi> of the potables of the nutritive juyce and blood thence made (to which poſſibly may be added the conſideration of ſome obſtructions in, or errors of the ferment of the liver) whereby the ſmall veſſels become ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and the ſeparation of the latex prevented, whence upon the regurgita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſuperfluous latex (ready to be ſeparated) back into the blood, and thence into the habit of the body, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens that Species of a <hi>Dropſie</hi> called <hi>Anaſarcoſis,</hi> which by the <hi>anaſtomoſis</hi> of the veſſels or concatenation of the <hi>limphiducts,</hi> lets part thereof fall into the legs, ſwelling them, eſpecially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards night, and at other times re-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibes or ſwallows it up again into the former cavities of the larger veſſels, and the leggs become unſwelled again.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:33968:57"/>
            <p>Or <hi>Secondly,</hi> The liquid potables (or ſuperfluous latex) by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid or equivalent obſtructions as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered flowing back, and heaped up moſtwhat betwixt the <hi>Omentum</hi> and <hi>Peritoneum,</hi> gives that ſpecies peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Hydrops,</hi> (properly a <hi>Dropſie</hi>) which ſtretching the aforeſaid membrans, bears up ſtrongly againſt the <hi>Diaphragme,</hi> thereby contracting the cavity of the lungs, hinder the due motion of the muſcles thereof, ſtraitens reſpiration, making the Patient ſhort winded as uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they are. Or <hi>laſtly,</hi> The ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted potable latex as conſidered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a flatulency, gives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that third ſpecies of a <hi>Dropſie</hi> we call a <hi>Tympany,</hi> which regurgitated la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tex hath for the moſt part no urinous Salt in it, whence thoſe who are tap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for dropſies, commonly weep forth an almoſt inſipid liquor, ſo alſo that water which paſſeth from thoſe who drink plentifully of the <hi>Spaw</hi> has no urinous Salt, neither tincture nor <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the next place we conſider how theſe waters (with ſome other addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional helps) work, and how they may thence anſwer the general indications of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33968:57"/>theſe ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Dropſies,</hi> and the ſymptoms thence emerging, will doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs covince us of the truth of what we are treating, (eſpecially if thereto be added) as a ſealing argument, (matter of fact) <hi>viz.</hi> firſt, that they chiefly rectify and ſtrengthen the ferment of the Stomach and thence take off the two attending ſymptoms of heat and thirſt, (all <hi>Dropſical</hi> Perſons generally having a <hi>febricula</hi> and thirſt upon them). And Secondly, That they (by reaſon of the <hi>Mineral</hi> Salts (wherewith they are acuated) may, and do hew forth their own way, open obſtructions, ſweeten or alter the tranſmiſſed <hi>Acidum</hi> and ſet open thoſe formerly dammed or blocked up water-ſluces, whereby the watery latex (lately through obſtructions heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up the blood, (and carried into other wrong veſſels) almoſt drowning and ſuffocating the vital ferment thereof, is now drawn or filtred off, and percola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through its proper veſſels, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exhauſted, the blood is reduced to its due craſis, and the tone of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitated <hi>viſcera,</hi> are by the gentle aſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of the inate Salts, fortified and rendred capable of performing their due ſecluſions and ſeparations, and the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33968:58"/>obſtructions of the Liver (if any ſuch there happen in the Fabrick of this Diſeaſe) or wrong caſt in its ferment, are hereby opened and rectified, and all the ſymptoms go off if the ferments be not too degenerate, and the latex too much depraved, and bowels tainted, (whence ſhortly will happen a total ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the blood and drowning of the Spirits in the flood) through the long continuance thereof; for thoſe who die of <hi>Dropſies,</hi> are (as we could eaſily ſhew) really drowned, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the ſame which happens by drowing in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter externally happens inwardly in the veſſels in dropſical dying perſons, by intercepting the circulation of the blood and drowning the Spirits, what we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay upon this ſubject, the reader may conſult our ſubject, the reader may conſult our <hi>Hydrolog. Chym.</hi> 117.118. &amp;c. to which (for brevity ſake) we refer; and ſhall content our ſelves at preſent, to confirm the truth of what is already ſaid by matter of fact from ſome few Inſtances, which are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:33968:58"/>
               <head>The Firſt Cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Th. Weſled</hi> of <hi>Grimsby</hi> in <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln-ſhire,</hi> was taken with an extreme pain in his belly, which held him for many months together, ſo as he could never ſay he was an hour free, which took away his ſleep, he was alſo ſwelled in his belly, as that he could not walk twenty yards without a reſt, and great difficutly of breathing, and continual ſneeſing; his appetite to meat was gone, ſo as he was deſpaired of by his Phyſicians, who ſuſpected a <hi>Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> he came to the waters, though with great difficulty in his Journey, becauſe of the weight of his belly, and drank near three weeks, and found an abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all the aforeſaid ſymptoms, the ſecond year perfected the cure; the third year he alſo drank the waters, which he continued to do, to prevent a relapſe, being then as healthful as in all his life before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:33968:59"/>
               <head>The Second Cure.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TH. Kud</hi>'s daughter in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> of about twelve years of age, had an inveterate <hi>Itch,</hi> and by a <hi>Chirurgeon Quack</hi> was fluxed for it, but in ſtead of curing her left her worſe; heightned the <hi>Scorbutick</hi> taint into a white leprous Scab all over her body, and her body ſwelled much, was very ſtark and hard, her legs ſwelled and her face huffed up, was judged by many incurable; I order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her a purge, which carried off much watery humors and made way for the waters; of which I ordered her to drink every morning; in each firſt pint in a morning (or ſometimes in a little warm Ale) to take one ounce of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup <hi>de Spina Cervina,</hi> alſo ordered her a gliſter <hi>ex recentis urinae,</hi> ℥xij <hi>cum Syr. de Spina Cervina,</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>x. and when I ſaw her four dayes after, I could ſcarce know her, in that her face was ſo much fallen and come to its right proportion, alſo her body was much unſwelled, as likewiſe her leggs, yea, was quite reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and continued ſo, as I had an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof from an ingenious friend who had it from her own Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:33968:59"/>
               <head>The Third Cure.</head>
               <p>MRS. <hi>Eliz. Turner</hi> of <hi>Hutton-pag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> through ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, fell into a great ſwelling, and hardneſs of her belly, with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of breathing, which gave too much cauſe to ſuſpect a <hi>Dropſie:</hi> It had reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Medicines, till coming to the waters, which ſhe drank fourteen days, her bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fell, and and ſhe ſhortly after concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with Child.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Worms.</head>
            <p>THE cauſes of <hi>Worms</hi> are chiefly aſcribable, firſt to the debilitude of the ferments, and next to the depravation and putrefaction of the nutritive juyces chiefly reſiding in the Stomach and Guts, which two cauſes joyntly conſidered, are doubtleſs the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries of worms and wormatick mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: For we ſee that Worms happen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally in Children, where the ferments
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33968:60"/>are not ſtrong, and whoſe nutritive juyces are hence apt to grow putrid, and prone to a ſpurious animation (if I may ſo ſay) the generation of worms, being a baſtardly product or off-ſet ſpringing from depraved vital ſeeds animating a degenerate putrid matter. Theſe without peradventure are many times the cauſes of ſeveral Diſeaſes (attended with bad ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms) even in <hi>adult</hi> perſons whoſe original frequently lies in obſcurity, and hence are apt to be miſtaken for other diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>That theſe waters expell worms and wormatick degenerate matter, both as it ſtrengthens the ferments, (helps di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion) and likewiſe reſiſts putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will partly be evident from the few following inſtances.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Firſt Cure.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RIchard Legard</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> had been many years troubled with ſmall worms which we call <hi>Ascarides,</hi> for which he had taken good advice, and uſed ſeveral remedies, yet never found any ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfull as theſe waters, which brought
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33968:60"/>from him, to his beſt judgment above five hundred in a day, and in a few days quit him both of the Worms and the matter that bred them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The ſecond cure.</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>G. Watſon</hi> of <hi>Throſhenby</hi> near <hi>Scarbrough</hi> was grievouſly affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with <hi>Melancholick</hi> fumes, which exceedingly clouded his underſtanding, and poſſeſſed him with fears and fancies, taking away his ſleep for many weeks together, ſo as he was become a meer <hi>Skelleton,</hi> and ſo feeble that he was not able to walk, but was carried about in arms, during which time he had never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs an incredible appetite, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a gnawing pain at his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, the cauſe of which diſtemper was not eaſily diſcerned, till after ſome time he began to void a ſort of flat worms about an inch long, empty as if they had been nothing but a skin, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying himſelf to the waters, he voided ſometimes thirty or forty in a day, and in a little time, found perfect cure, all ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms abating, and his appetite retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to its regular courſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:33968:61"/>
            <head>Womens Diſeaſes.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WOmens</hi> Diſeaſes peculiarly ſo called, are ſuch as properly belong to the womb, and to its <hi>Regimen</hi> and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities which chiefly either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the obſtructions of the <hi>Matrix,</hi> whereby the redundant ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous blood, (to be ſeparated accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the due courſe of nature in the forms of the Menſes) flows back, floats in the containing veſſels, in this or the other part, whom with its plenty it ſtretcheth (whence as an <hi>aliquid am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius</hi>) a turgeſcence, and plethory, and the ſymptoms thence following; or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a debilitude of the womb, whereby the blood becomes drained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in too great quantities, whence <hi>Lypothymia</hi>'s, Faintings, Swoonings, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As to the former; in order to the better underſtanding of what the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of the womb are, and what the effects thence enſuing towards a right apprehenſion (I ſay) whereof
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33968:61"/>we ſhew in our <hi>Hydrolog. Chym.</hi> what the <hi>Menſtrua</hi> are, the manner of their Generation, their uſe in nature, their lunar and critical ſeaſons of Evacuation, and how from their obſtruction ariſe a <hi>Plethora</hi> (beſides what happens at every natural and critical Evacuation) and how the effects of which (if ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the head) are uſually (if inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal) Megrim, Dizzineſs, or pain in the head, or (if external) are puſtles in the face, redneſs and ſoreneſs of eyes, ſwelling of the face, &amp;c. if in other places, thence tumors, erratick pains, and how from the reſtagnation of the blood (through the aforeſaid obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) in the Bronchys of the Lungs, happen indiſpoſitions, dulneſs and ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſs of the body, ſhortneſs of breath, oppreſſion of the Precordia, or upper mouth of the Stomach, &amp;c. concerning all which (I ſay) we treat in our <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drolog. Chym.</hi> p. 125. 126. &amp;c. to which we refer.</p>
            <p>We ſhall only here add, that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (by their connate Salts) are (by matter of fact) found, not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for opening obſtructions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently adapted for the helping ſuch Diſeaſes and Symptoms as thence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33968:62"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Green-ſickneſs</hi> in Maids, the fits of the <hi>Mother,</hi> and ſymptoms thence ariſing; But alſo (by obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) are found, as effectual by its gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle aſtingency, to repreſs the overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings both white and red, whoſe floods otherwiſe bring on Lypothymia's, Faintings, Swoonings, &amp;c. For though it be an apperient water, yet with other proper adviſable helps, it is found by experience, notably to ſtay the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Fluxes of Women.</p>
            <p>As to the Firſt, the waters (with other additional helps) are powerful in opening (as I ſaid) obſtructions, the <hi>Minera</hi> or ſource of womens Maladies, makes the blood well to circulate, and duly to pay its <hi>Lunar</hi> or Monethly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, cauſing right ſeparations to be made, whereby their ſhortneſs of breath leave them, their liſtleſneſs and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedneſs goes off, and all other bad ſymptomes aforeſaid diſappear, their appetite and digeſtion comes on, grow vigorous, well complexioned, get a good colour for what they do: making them look of a ruddy and freſh complexion, where nature her ſelf thus aſſiſted, begins to paint, whoſe colours (being only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered by an inviſible pencil) are
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33968:62"/>not only moſt lively, but alſo durable, and conſequently (if other features conſpire) the beſt and moſt taking.</p>
            <p>And withal to ſuch as are apt to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, they notably ſtrengthen the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive faculty of the womb, helping ſuch to go on to their time.</p>
            <p>And that it takes away ſome cauſes of barrenneſs, being frequently found to further conception, both in thoſe who having been long married, never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and in ſuch as, after many years of intermiſſion, near paſt all hopes of more children: In both which caſes let the following Inſtances ſerve for the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prolifickneſs</hi> of the Waters, or Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the waters efficacy towards help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of conception.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The firſt Caſe</head>
               <p>MR. <hi>Th.</hi> St. <hi>Quintin,</hi> of <hi>Flambrough</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> and his Wife, were ſeven years and an half married, during which time ſhe had never conceived, upon the report of the efficacy and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the waters, he brought her to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> where ſhe drank fourteen
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33968:63"/>dayes, within a month after ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and brought forth a Son. Then having an interruption for four years, he brought her to the waters again: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a fortnight or three weeks that ſhe had left the waters, ſhe conceived again; and brought forth a Daughter: both which (at the firſt writing hereof) were living and healthful Children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Second Caſe.</head>
               <p>MRs. <hi>Elizabeth Turner</hi> of <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Pagnel</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> whoſe cure of the <hi>Dropſie</hi> by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is formerly mentioned; ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, ſhe conceived with Child, and brought forth a Son, having had no child before of ſeven years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Third Caſe.</head>
               <p>MRS. <hi>Elizabeth Smith</hi> of <hi>Scremer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham,</hi> whoſe cure of <hi>Hypochondriack Melancholy</hi> is before recited, upon which it hapned alſo that while ſhe was with her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> ſhe conceived with
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33968:63"/>Child, when as yet to her own expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhe was paſt hopes of any more children, having never conceived for above five years before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fourth Caſe.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Scotch</hi> Gentlewo-man, being in years, whoſe cure of <hi>Hypocondraick Melancholy</hi> and the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, upon which, drinking the waters (notwithſtanding the great weakneſs ſhe was reduced to) ſhe conceived and brought forth two Children, which was wonderfull ſo weak a woman as ſhe was ſhould conceive or bring them forth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judged ſo weak, as not capable of bringing forth one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Fifth Caſe.</head>
               <p>SR. <hi>H. Thompſon</hi> his Lady had no Child by two former Husbands when Sr. <hi>H.</hi> married her, ſhe came to the waters, whereupon conceived</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:33968:64"/>
               <p>Among the Claſſis of Diſeaſes belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Womb, may not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently be reckoned ſuch ſwellings of the belly, as happen ſometimes from cold upon or after Child-bearing, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which we have one conſiderable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the efficacy of theſe waters, as followeth.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>G. Tunſtal</hi> of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> his wives belly never fell after a Child ſhe had born, nor could he by all the means he uſed, take it down; The Phyſician then at the <hi>Spaw, viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Wittie</hi> was conſulted, who adviſed her Husband to give her ſome preparatives, and ſomething elſe with the water to further the intention, after a few dayes her Boddice did lace cloſe, that could not meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three or four inches before, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to drink a moneth, and returned perfectly well, and ſo continued free from all ſwelling, it being (at the firſt writing hereof) neer three years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>To which may be added, that theſe waters are very effectual in the cure of all ſuch ſymptomatical Diſeaſes (if I may ſo call them) which take their firſt original from obſtructions of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33968:64"/>menſtrual evacuation, <hi>viz. epileptick, paralytick, apoplectick, hyſterick, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſive asthmatick Affections;</hi> That is, thoſe Diſeaſes in women, which (from the aforeſaid cauſes) moſt reſemble the <hi>Falling-Sickneſs, Palſies, Apoplexies,</hi> fits of the <hi>Mother, Convulſions,</hi> and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of <hi>breathing,</hi> or diſeaſes deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the aforeſaid Spring-head, which by their penetrating Salts open obſtructions (the <hi>Minera</hi> of ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies) and remove the firſt cauſes thereof, whereby (together with the addition of other ſpecifick helps) all the aforeſaid Symptomatick or ſecondary Diſeaſes will neceſſarily and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ceaſe, concerning all which we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe more largely in our <hi>Hydrologia Chym.</hi> p. 84. 94. 95. to which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:33968:65"/>
            <head>An Impoſthume.</head>
            <p>THat theſe waters are powerful in breaking and carrying away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Impoſthumations,</hi> I ſhall give one conſiderable Inſtance.</p>
            <p>In the year 74. or 75. a man who had an <hi>Impoſthumation</hi> in his ſmall guts, drank the waters, and in a few dayes after the firſt drinking thereof, while he had a ſtool, he obſerved ſomething to give a crack, the <hi>Impoſthume</hi> broke and came all away, the matter was lodged in a <hi>skin</hi> or <hi>film,</hi> which he ſhewed a Merchant (my worthy friend and late patient) here upon the <hi>Sands,</hi> who gave me the relation thereof, as an eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having</hi> thus run through the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Chronick</hi> Diſeaſes, and ſhewed the great efficacy of the waters (ſometimes accommodated with other appropriate helps) in order to their reſpective cures we would conclude with ſome remarks of their vertue in the cure of Acute Diſeaſes, <hi>viz.</hi> contined <hi>Feavers,</hi> as to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33968:65"/>which, we eſteem them (duly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred) among the beſt ſort of purges, and greatly conducible towards the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating of the ſpurious <hi>febrile</hi> fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or praeternatural boyling of the blood, and one of the beſt quenchers of thirſt we know of in the World, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtrangely allaying the <hi>Luxuriant</hi> ſymptoms of a <hi>Feaver,</hi> even although, in ſome caſes, extended to a <hi>Dilirium</hi> or <hi>Frenzie,</hi> of which we ſhall give this following remakable Inſtance as I had it from the Gentlemans own mouth <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Alderman of <hi>York</hi> went to drink theſe waters for a debilitude of the <hi>Anus,</hi> whoſe Muſcles (from ſome <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick Acidum</hi> fixed there) was ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxed, and the tone of the parts ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and enfeebled as was a very great affliction to him, he for a time ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed drinking the waters, and what through the pain of the grieved parts, and what through an inquietude and reſtleſneſs (which yet was conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to the former) and perhaps partly through an imbibition of the <hi>Scorbutick Acidum</hi> into the blood, begot ſuch an alteration of the <hi>Craſis</hi> thereof as he fell into a <hi>Feaver,</hi> whoſe ſymptoms pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33968:66"/>ſo ſtrongly, and grew ſo high, that it brought a <hi>Dilirium</hi> or <hi>Frenzy</hi> upon him, he was forbidden to drink the waters; but notwithſtanding which injunction and impoſition, he ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red privately, which none knew, ſtole a hearty drink, took two luſty pulls at a whole pitcher of the waters (left by a water-woman) which wrought excellently well with him, allayed his thirſt, took away his <hi>Dilirium</hi> or <hi>Frenzy;</hi> yea, ſo took off the bad ſymptoms of his <hi>Feaver,</hi> as that he ſpeedily recovered, came down out of his Chamber, and was the very next day (if I do not miſ-remember) as well as any of the reſt of the company.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:33968:66"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe of an <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Sulphur-Bath,</hi> and <hi>Bath of Sea-water,</hi> with the uſes thereof in the Cure of <hi>ſeveral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving a Diſcourſe of the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur Bath</hi> at <hi>Knarsbrough,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready Extant, at the heel of our <hi>Zymol. Phyſ.</hi> or Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Diſcourſe of Fermentation, which we judged as a neceſſary Appendix to our two former Treatiſes of the <hi>Spaw</hi>'s viz. <hi>Hydrolog. Chymic.</hi> and <hi>Hydrolog.</hi> Eſſays; we have therein (which may be ſomewhat <hi>preluminary</hi> or <hi>introductory</hi> to this) traced this following Method, in the ſeven or eight enſuing particular Heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt.</hi> By laying down the conſtitutive ingredients and Mineral principles of that water.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly.</hi> By ſhewing the Proceſs (as near as we can apprehend) nature uſeth
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33968:67"/>in the preparing that excellent water.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly.</hi> By ſhewing the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt it and natural hot Baths in their original and imbred principles, ſo alſo in ſome ſort as to their virtues.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fourthly.</hi> By pointing out how and by what means, the <hi>Sulphur</hi> (as the chief Mineral ingredient of that water) is ſo opened as to become not only ſo ſubtill as thence to be ſolvable therein <hi>odore te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> but alſo ſo volatile as to paſs off in a continual ſteam and inſenſible <hi>Effluvium.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fifthly.</hi> By ſhewing how this <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> water comes not much ſhort as to its original principles, nor is much (if at all) inferiour in efficacy to ſome other <hi>Sulphur</hi> waters, which are hot Baths, in as much as that it's lately found ſucceſsful for outward applications, as well as thoſe by late obſervation are remarked for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward uſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sixthly.</hi> By ſhewing that the artificial heating of the <hi>Sulphur.</hi> water bears ſome Analogy to the in-bred heat of other Baths, as they come hot out of the earth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Seventhly.</hi> By pointing out how Art may imitate Nature (yet from the ſame principles) in the reſemblance of moſt Baths, <hi>viz.</hi> how to prepare ſuch Baths Artificially as are Natural.</item>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:33968:67"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Laſtly.</hi> By inquiring how and after what manner that <hi>Sulphur</hi>-water per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms thoſe expected helps as a <hi>Bath,</hi> where in ſhort its various virtues are unfolded in order to the help of ſeveral Diſeaſes; for illuſtration of which, we refer to that Diſcourſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But the Reader may object and ſay, that all here ſaid relates to the <hi>Sulphur</hi>-water, and the virtues aſcribable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, may only belong to it as ſuch? The anſwer to which objection opens a door to let me in to ſay in this matter what I chiefly aim at.</p>
            <p>And <hi>firſt,</hi> That Art working with the ſame inſtruments that Nature doth, is ſo far from perverting the courſe of nature, as it rather promotes the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> That what is done by Art above ground with congeneal principles, in imitation of what is performed in the bowels of the earth by the Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Nature, muſt needs be congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and very ſutable to nature, ſo that if nature be traced in her <hi>ſubterraneal</hi> ſolutions, praecipitations, percolations, and other manner of depurations, and that by various Salts or other Mineral juyces in order to the preparing Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33968:68"/>healing waters; what ſhould hinder (even in a rational way) but that by skilfull Enkeireſy or manual (admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting analogy in Principles) the ſame may be done above ground, and that for the ſupplying other places by a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign hand where nature is defective, not but that in ſome caſes we muſt own the curioſity of Nature to be ſuch as cannot be imitated, and her paths ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure as are indiſcoverable by our dull ſenſes, ſo that in ſuch productions where Nature is imitable, if we arrive at due Mediums and proſecute them with parallel circumſtances, we need not doubt of reaching equivalent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</p>
            <p>But in ſhort, we propoſe to ſhew, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The poſſibility of preparing ſuch an artificial Bath, as may (for ought we know) in every reſpect (or at leaſt in ſuch as we have need of) anſwer the Natural. And next to ſhew its uſes; The firſt we diſcover in our aforeſaid Treatiſe, and intend (if God grant life and health) to have ready for uſe againſt the <hi>Spaw</hi> ſeaſon, to render it practical as (among other things) a neceſſary adjunct for the benefit of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:33968:68"/>
            <p>And here (for brevity ſake) as <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liminary</hi> to the latter, becauſe the uſes of the Sea-Bath and artificial <hi>Sulphur</hi>-Bath will be reciprocal according as the judgement of the Phyſician guided by indications of Diſeaſes ſhall adviſe, ſometimes the one, other-while the other <hi>prore nata,</hi> as the caſe ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, therefore what relates to the help or cure of ſuch Diſeaſes as are peculiar to either or both, we ſhall (to avoid mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of words) reduce under one name, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Bath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore as to the latter (which is what we mainly aim at) <hi>viz.</hi> the uſes of the Bath, we propoſe it as effectual (together with other concurring helps) chiefly in ſuch Diſeaſes as ariſe; firſt, from the ill habit of the <hi>genus nervoſum</hi> (or nervous parts) <hi>viz. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexy</hi>'s, <hi>Palſie</hi>'s, <hi>Falling-ſickneſs,</hi> and <hi>Convulſions,</hi> the particular accounts whereof we (for brevity ſake) new omit, next to which we might reckon upon the <hi>Gout,</hi> and <hi>Sciatica,</hi> (which are the ſame Diſeaſe, only diſtinguiſhed by difference of parts affected) which in as much as it chiefly conſiſts in a ſpuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ferment or (if I may ſo call it) Stum of the blood, tranſmitted upon
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33968:69"/>the <hi>Synovia</hi> or <hi>interior</hi> membrane of the joynts (that exquiſitly ſenſible web woven over the whole,) made up of nervous fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres whence the ſenſible pains eſſentially inherent in that Malady, thence theſe <hi>Sulphurious Baths</hi> (with other helps) are found proper in the dinting and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying the aforeſaid fermental acoras, matter of fact hath already evinced. To which may be added the <hi>Rickets</hi> and other weakneſſes of joynts in chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as alſo all <hi>Scorbutick</hi> impurities, <hi>Itch</hi> or <hi>Scabs,</hi> or other foulneſſes of the skin, all which by a skilfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement it takes off, opening the pores of the skin, giving liberty for the blood to breath forth what is noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to it, and dints all bad ferments lodged in the outward parts, as to which we have not time now to inlarge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:33968:69"/>
            <head>The <hi>Rarities</hi> obſervable at <hi>Scarbrough.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO ranck what is here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable into their ſeveral claſſes, and to treat diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of them would ſwell this Piece beyond its intended bounds, therefore we ſhall at preſent only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with this ſlight method <hi>(viz.) Firſt,</hi> To reckon up the ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Diureticks</hi> becauſe thoſe are very uſeful for the help of Mankind, next to touch upon Stones with ſome hints of the variety thereof: Then to ſpeak and that very conciſely by way of Epitome, of Sea-plants, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As to the Firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Some excellent <hi>Diureticks</hi> of which four ſorts are here found.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is the Mineral Fountain it ſelf, which by daily experience is found to be a moſt admirable <hi>Diuretick,</hi> generally paſſing well, and carrying off with it that mucous or viſcous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is often the cauſe of obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and difficulty of Urine; as alſo
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33968:70"/>Sabulous matter, which concreted, ſwells into larger ſtones, (and which the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (if not of a very hard or compleat texture) will diſſolve, or if confirmed (and not too bigg for the paſſages) will bring away.</p>
            <p>The Second <hi>Diuretick</hi> is <hi>Daucus Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtris,</hi> which grows within a dozen yards or thereabouts off the <hi>Spaw,</hi> ſeems as if placed there deſignedly by Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to fortifie and ſecond the <hi>Diure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> quality of the <hi>Mineral</hi> waters. That what Nature works under ground by <hi>Minerals</hi> exquiſitely contempering and diſſolving them and their Salts in water, is here alſo wrought in another Kingdom (even the vegitable) above ground, evident not only in that of the <hi>Daucus,</hi> but alſo in the production of another moſt excellent <hi>Diuretick</hi> plant (to be found upon <hi>Scarbrough</hi>-Caſtle-Banks) called <hi>Carduns-Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> of great efficacy, as has been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in the cure of the Stone,</p>
            <p>And as though theſe were not enough to afford ſuch admirable Specificks, wherein, as if not only the <hi>Mineral</hi> Kingdom in the <hi>Subterraneal</hi> Soluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof (evident in this apperient Spring) but alſo the workings of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33968:70"/>above ground, apparent in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable Kingdom (as aforeſaid) were I ſay, not ſufficient; Nature to compleat her number in the ternary of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, adds the Animal and therein exhibits to our view the largeſt ſort of <hi>Milipides</hi> that ever I ſaw, a kind of Animal or rather Inſect, which are bred and live amongſt the Rocks of this place, they conſiſt of a curious texture of parts very bright and an almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible ſize, of which we have gotten ſeveral a compleat Inch long. They ſeem to be an animation of Marine Salt foſtering their oviperous original, excited by a ſtony Fracedo incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Sun-beams, and to be fed thereby, whence their great plenty of an inbred volatile <hi>Alkali,</hi> the Marine Salt in the Fabrick of their bodies, by the ferment thereof, (like as if by an Animal <hi>Alkaheſt,</hi>) being tranſmuted into an <hi>Alkali,</hi> or from fixt is made volatile, ſuch energy there is in Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ferments, whence theſe Inſects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come powerful Abſterſives and openers of obſtructions both in the caſe of the <hi>Jaundies,</hi> as alſo againſt difficulty of Urine.</p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:33968:71"/>
            <p>The next thing we propoſe in order is concerning Stones, where in, the firſt place, amongſt thoſe Rocks on the back of the Caſtle, we take notice of ſome ſtrange and myſtical inſcriptions written in large Characters by another hand than we are uſually acquainted with, where he who is skilful in the language of Nature in the unfolding the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thereof, has by theſe dark <hi>Hyero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicks,</hi> a leſſon hard enough ſet him.</p>
            <p>To ſee ſome <hi>Pyrites</hi> or fire-ſtones (ſome call thunderbolts) incloſed in other textured rocky ſtones, ſo ſhaped and figured as if ſhot in by ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen hand, as well as inviſible bow; which (although both are Stone) yet the former as much differs from the ſtony ſoyl of the latter they are planted or grow in, as a vegitable plant differs from the earth it ſprings from, ſuch an object I ſay can beget no leſs than wonder. To ſee (by viewing again) Cockle or Muſcle-ſhells incloſed in great bulky ſtones (as Hetrogeneous parts which conſtitute the whole compage) and ſome of them to become as ſtony as the Rock they are fixed in. To ſee others, <hi>viz.</hi> Cockles in their intire form incloſed in and perfectly walled
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33968:71"/>about which leſſer ſtones like as if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in ſtony baggs or petrifick caſes. Alſo to view other ſtones (there found) like boulders to incloſe the perfectly wrought bodies of Snakes or Serpents Spirally wrought up in a ſmall compaſs, where the Snake ſtone has leſt ſuch an impreſſion upon its caſe or print as if it had been the mould, about which clay or ſome ſucculent ſtone had been ſo wrought and then hardned or petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Salt-water and niterous air, and thence had received impreſſion juſt as boys do in making their prints of clay upon moulds, and to ſee the great variety of curious Stones thrown upon the Sands; ſome like <hi>Diamonds,</hi> others like <hi>Aggates,</hi> and ſo of other colours, of which ſome have been ſold at great rates. To conclude, to ſee great ſtones cruſted over with fiſh-ſhells, as if nature was cloathing them with new coats; all which, beſides matter of common won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, may alſo give occaſion to the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt in his allotting of the cauſes of things, to think again. To go in the next place and view thoſe pretty little guardens of Natures own ſowing plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and walling: To ſee I ſay, little Woods and Trees curiouſly branched,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:33968:72"/>each ſmall twig and ſlender <hi>fibre</hi> born up and delicately diſplayed to full view, painted in their natural colours, inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſtone, growing in <hi>Neptunes</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and ſwimming in a flood; I mean and ſome other <hi>Coraline</hi> plants whoſe roots are fixed upon ſtones, incircled with walls made of the ſame, floating in Sea-water, exhibiting various co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, no leſs pleaſurable to the eye, then ſatisfactory to a curious ſearching mind: To ſay nothing here of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that great variety of Sea-plants which challenge the Rocks and Sea for their ſoyl, here to be ſeen, of which I have beſtowed pains in making a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, as the curious at the ſeaſon may view. All which cannot but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get admiration, which if it do not, it is a firm argument of the hardneſs and ſtonineſs of that mind as well as of its petrifique objects.</p>
            <p>To ſay little here of the two Wells or Springs of freſh waters which ariſe pretty near day, upon the high Rock on which the Caſtle ſtands, one of which is within two or three yards of the very brink of that ſteep Rock which bounds the Sea, which is a vaſt heighth above the Surface of <hi>Neptunes</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33968:72"/>Element, and theſe Springs are rarely (even in the greateſt droughts) known to fail.—And near to this place <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>Whitby</hi> are the great <hi>Allom-works</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> of which we have given ſome account in our <hi>Hydrolog.</hi> Eſſayes.</p>
            <p>To ſee each <hi>Proſelite</hi> to Natures Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſearching for Rarities upon the Sea-ſhore, and every one like another <hi>Archimedes,</hi> returning with his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in one thing or other, either ſome cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſtones, or ſome Marcaſite with a Cockle or Serpent wrapt therein, which when the petrifick ſhell is broke, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear plain to view in their intire and curious form, or ſome pretty Sea-Plant; for after every flood, a new ſcene of <hi>Rarities</hi> in one ſort or other appears, where are to be ſeen thoſe <hi>Ludicra Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> in which Nature ſports her ſelf in great variety.</p>
            <p>To conclude, Methinks the queſtion concerning every <hi>Rarity</hi> we here meet with, is not much unlike that of our Lords to them who tempted him about the Lawfulneſs of paying Tribute, <hi>viz.</hi> whoſe Superſcription is upon it, or whoſe Image doth it bear? And the anſwer thereto not different from theirs, <hi>viz. Caeſars,</hi> that of the great King,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:33968:73"/>of Heaven and Earth; who as he hath ſtamped the character of his Wiſdom and power upon every created viſible object, ſo more particularly ſome things ſeem to bear bolder ſhadows of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Pencil, and to retain more vigorous impreſſions and lively draughts of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage thereof. And laſtly, The concluſion or genuine conſequence of both, runs parallel with that of our Lords advice, <hi>viz.</hi> to give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things which belong to <hi>Caeſar, viz.</hi> Admiration, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration, Obedience and Praiſes for ever, and all the World to come in with full <hi>Chorus,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Amen, Hallelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33968:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
